hello everybody my name is Angelo and I
am your emcee for the evening and on
behalf of the UBC free speech club we
would like to welcome you and thank you
for attending our third dr. Jordan B
Peterson event now I know you're all
very excited to hear the man so I'm
gonna keep these opening remarks very
short the UBC free speech Club is
devoted to the sanctity of Liberty in
our society and the necessity to keep
Liberty safe from those who want to
destroy it within just the year our club
has grown to over a thousand members and
is now in the process of incorporation
so that we may continue to bring
speakers and host events such as this
one
none of that would be possible without
dr. Peterson who has inspired countless
students all over North America to start
speaking up on their campus and in fact
this club sprung up around the same time
when dr. Peterson publicly came out
against the bill c16 that was just over
a year ago and since then his philosophy
of cleaning your room and sorting
yourself out has bettered and influenced
the lives of countless people he's an
accomplished psychologist professor and
author his book maps of meaning is an
analytical window into the myths and
cultures of humankind and now he has
written a new book it's called twelve
rules for life and antidote to chaos and
is available for pre-order on Amazon
with the release date of January 23 2018
and on that note on behalf of the UBC
free speech club we would like to
introduce you all to dr. Jordan B
Peterson
[Applause]
well thank you very much for that that's
that's quite something all right
there's a house Mike great I don't need
this one okay well then let's just move
it out of the way great so I'm gonna
talk to you tonight about the
ideological nexus of post-modernism and
Marxism and I want to get into it fairly
deeply so you can have a thoughtful
thoughtful talk and then discussion
afterwards so it's a confusing topic
because it's not obvious by any stretch
of the imagination why post-modernism
and and Neel Marxism or Marxism proper
would be aligned because post-modernism
is an anti grand narrative philosophical
movement and Marxism is a grand
narrative and so the fact that those two
things seem to coexist in the same space
needs definitely need some explanation
and it's a very tricky thing to get to
the bottom of so we won't get to the
bottom of it but we'll get farther to
the bottom of it then I've got before
and hopefully farther than many of you
have got before so let's see what we can
figure out here so I'm gonna start with
some some definitions hmm I'll return to
them as we continue you know with
philosophical movements then they're
often not named by the major thinkers in
the movement they're sort of named
afterwards the name covers a very large
range of ideas and actions and
perceptions like it's not that easy
people talk about existentialism for
example it's not that easy to come up
with a one paragraph summary of what
constitutes existentialism my sense for
the existentialist is that it's a it's
it's fundamentally a movement that's
predicated on the idea at least in in
this psychological sense that you know
Freud tended to attribute human
suffering and mental disorder to
hood trauma it's more complex than that
but that'll do for a for a quick
overview but the existentialists thought
that there was enough suffering
intrinsic in life so that it wasn't
insanity that was the question it was
sanity it was how was possible for
people to be sane and and and and let's
say normal for lack of a better word
given that there was brutality and
malevolence intrinsic in life and the
fact that you had to rise up as an
individual and and stand in relation to
that relationship to that is part and
parcel of what constitutes
existentialism there's all sorts of
different people who were thinkers who
were existentialist some of them
atheistic some of them deeply religious
like Dostoyevsky but so it's not I'm
using that as an example to show you how
difficult it is to bring a set of
thinkers under one umbrella you're bound
to oversimplify but we'll go ahead and
oversimplify post-modernism you can
think about it as an attitude of
skepticism irony towards and rejection
of grand narratives ideologies and
universalism including the idea of the
objective notions of reason that's a big
one human nature that's a big one social
progress absolute truth and object of
reality all those things being
questioned I kind of think of the head
Joker at the top of the postmodern
hierarchy as Derrida Foucault is often
mentioned as are a number of other
people here's some other attributes of
postmodern thinking there's a
recognition of the existence of
hierarchy that's for sure and there's an
echo of that idea the recognition of
hierarchy and the term patriarchy
because of course patriarchy is a
recognition of hierarchy now it's a very
particular kind of recognition but the
post modernists also tend to define
hierarchy as a consequence of power
differential and so the world they
envision as far as I can tell is
something like a it's a sociological II
Hobbesian nightmare
so hobbes thought of the philosopher
Thomas Hobbes thought of
the natural state of human beings as
every individual in some sense at the
throat of every other individual so that
the basic state of man mankind
unlike the Rousseau lien state of say
virgin innocence and and and the
primitive garden of paradise was an
all-out war of everyone against everyone
else and that that required the
imposition of the social order to keep
peace essentially so it's a it's a
fairly dark view of of humankind
Rousseau on the other hand would think
of people as intrinsically good and the
social order as intrinsically tyrannical
you can actually think about Hobbes and
Rousseau in some sense of as as as
opposites that need to be paired
together in order to get a relatively
comprehensive view of human nature
well the postmodern view is like the
Hobbesian view in some sense except you
want to replace the individual with with
with pyramids of of social organization
so hierarchies of social organization
that are based on group identity and
that the landscape in which those
pyramids exist is one of unbroken enmity
and inability to communicate so it's a
very dark view as far as I'm concerned
and I think it's fundamentally wrong and
in many ways I mean it's right in that
there are groups of people and there is
some difficulty in communication between
them and that power is in the element in
the formation of hierarchies but you
can't reduce hierarchy or group
relationship to those premises it's too
simplified because people also cooperate
we're also not groups many many of us
belong to many groups so it's to the
actual situation is far too complex to
reduce it to that degree to reduce it to
that degree even though you can come up
with a good explanatory story if you do
so it doesn't capture the nuances and
they're not just nuances it doesn't
capture the essence now the thing is is
that when you make the presupposition
that the reason that hierarchies exist
is because of power then essentially
what you do is turn every hierarchy into
a tyranny and so if you if there is
hierarchy then you assume it's a tyranny
well that's really the patriarchy the
patriarchy is hierarchy assumed as
tyranny and that's also just not true
except in pathological hierarchies so
for example we know from the
psychological literature that the best
predictors of long-term life success our
intelligence and conscientiousness
in in Western countries at least well
that's what you'd hope for right more or
less if you want it even to set up a
society even if you weren't particularly
smart or hard-working you might want to
set up a society where intelligence and
hard work we're good predictors of
success because then the people who were
smart and hardworking would produce a
bunch of things that you could have if
you could trade for them and of course
that is actually the situation that most
of us are in so and of course the other
thing about people who believe that
hierarchies in the West are only
composed of of power and tyranny is that
their own actions belie that because
whenever they make a decision to
interact with that hierarchy they
attempt or to make a purchase or to make
a trade let's say or to obtain a server
a service of any importance let's say a
medical service they are going to
definitely act as if there are less and
more competent people within that
hierarchy and seek out the ones that are
more competent obviously which you don't
do if if the hierarchy is only composed
of tyranny and power there's no point
looking for competence but anyways in
the West and in functioning societies
the hierarchies are basically predicated
on competence and not power and and you
might say well that's pretty naive it's
like no actually it's not very naive I'm
not saying at all that inappropriate
power plays don't play a role in
corrupting hierarchies of competence
that happens but generally what happens
is if the hierarchies of competence get
corrupted enough by power then they
crumble because they can no longer
function so and though you know the
evidence that our hierarchies of
competence work is everywhere because
everything around us works all the time
ayaan Hirsi Ali tells that to to
interesting stories in her book infidel
which is a great book by the way she
came from Africa and and from a country
that wasn't very functional and when she
came to Holland
said there were two things that really
amazed her and this really struck me
because you know now and then you get
lucky and you can see the the world you
live in from an outsider's perspective
right you get to see through someone
else's eyes she said the first thing
that knocked her off her feet was
waiting for a bus in in Amsterdam and on
the you know she's standing at the bus
stop and there's a pole there and
there's digital sign on the pole and the
digital sign says when the next bus is
going to come and counts down and then
when it hits zero the bus appears and
she just she just she absolutely could
not believe that that would happen that
there could be a sign that told you when
the bus would come and that it would
change and the bus would actually appear
and you think well yeah no that's a
miracle man that's an absolute miracle
it is it is you've got to think that
through you know the amount of timing
and organization and and and reliability
mechanical reliability and sociological
or social organization and dedication on
the part of the bus drivers in the
entire company and the organization of
the whole city in the state to make that
possible is absolutely beyond belief
especially when it's time to well
perhaps not the second but to ten
seconds or something like that that is
absolutely beyond belief and her
inability to comprehend that was the
correct response and then the other
thing she was amazed by was that you
could go talk to policemen and they
would help you that was just that was
just a no-go for her because for her ik
her experience was policemen were there
to shake you down and and hurt you and
so you think well you know
well I won't I won't dwell on that point
any longer the point is is that it's
absolutely ridiculous blind to make the
assumption that the hierarchies in
functioning Western democracies are
fundamentally predicated on power and
tyranny and then you know I can use a
biological example to which would place
me outside of the postmodern realm of
argument because the post modernists
don't believe in biology but but they
act like they do because they all die so
so this primatologist named well I'll
tell you two stories okay cuz these are
these are really useful so the ones
about rats and I got this story from yok
panksepp who was a great neuroscientist
he wrote a book called effective
neuroscience which by the way is on my
reading list that's on my website it's a
really good book affective neuroscience
he's a great scientist he was one of the
people who he learned that he learned
that rats laugh they laugh out
ultrasonic li-like bats so if you're
gonna you tickle them with a pencil
eraser they laugh but you have to record
it and then slow it down and then you
can hear them and you might think well
rats laugh like what would be a big
grant for that what kind of idiocy is
that it's like no no no just don't don't
don't get ahead of yourself here you
know he was showing that that that
capacity for social interaction for
social interaction that was mediated by
physiological touch mmm-hmm activated
the same excuse me activated the same
circuits in rats that a dozen people and
that those are actual biological
circuits and that we share them even
with rats now rats are quite similar to
human beings as it turns out I could say
especially post modernists but I won't
and and and so the fact that that you
know that little rats giggle when you
tickle them is is actually
extraordinarily important he also
identified surprising I've been talking
too much lately he also identified the
primary play circuit in mammals and
that's a big deal too from a scientific
perspective that's like discovering a
new continent like discovering a whole
brain system that people really didn't
know existed that's a big deal
so here's a little story about rats so
young rats like to engage in
rough-and-tumble play especially
juvenile males it's also the case for
puppies if you've ever had a puppy
dogs are like that they like to wrestle
and it's one of the things that male
human beings tend to do with their
offspring and it's a really really good
thing like rough-and-tumble play with
children really help socialize them
because
helps them figure out the difference
between touch and even rough touch and
pain you know cuz one of the things
you're doing when you're rough and
tumble playing with the little kid is
you know you throw them up in the air
and you wrestle it around
I built my I had two couches when my
kids were little that were sort of face
to face so we built this little
wrestling ring and I used to go in there
and pound them half to death every night
you know
so they loved that I mean they get so
excited about that they love that so
much it's just crazy but the reason for
that is like you're stretching out their
bodies and you're showing them that they
can't put their thumb and your eye and
you're teaching them to be graceful and
and and you're teaching them the
difference between something new that's
happening to the body and something
painful you're really teaching them to
dance and it's this really complicated
physiological dance that that is
indicative of a socialized being and
that's partly why women like men who can
dance by the way because it seemed shows
that you can pay attention to someone
else first of all that you're
coordinated but even more importantly
that you can take the fact of your
coordination and coordinate that with
someone else's coordination so and
that's very primal and physiological
it's built right into your body
and rough and tumble play helps without
a lot anyways rats also like to rough
and tumble play for much the same
reasons and sort of sort of pretty much
all social mammals so you can tell that
rats like it see how do you know if a
rat like something well he'll work for
it and one of the ways you can figure
out if a rat wants to work for something
is that no you get him in a state where
maybe he's desperate for whatever he's
working for and you can put a little
spring on him and figure out how hard he
pulls to go somewhere he knows where
he's going to get that and then you can
measure the force that he's willing to
apply and that gives you a rough
estimate of his motivation or maybe
asked a bar press like a you know like a
coke cocaine addicted rat to to receive
the reward and you can count rate of bar
pressing and you can get an estimate of
how excited the rat is to go do whatever
it is the rats going to do and so
panksepp used to put rats
he'd pair them one rat against the other
in kind of a play arena not a very big
thing and and these were juvenile males
and they would work to do that okay so
they liked it and
and maybe one rat was 10% bigger than
the other and then when you paired them
the big rat would beat the little rat
because 10% weight advantage was enough
to make the bigger dominant okay so then
they established basically dominance and
Submission you might think about that as
a power relationship and to some degree
it is but it's more complicated than
that and this is very important so so
the rats play together once and the big
rat pins the little rat really very much
like wrestling those rats wrestle just
like people wrestle and if you pair them
together then the big rat can pin the
little rat okay so now you got dominant
rats subordinate rat roughly speaking
and but then you see if you stop the
experiment there you'd think while the
rats play to establish dominance and
Submission but the thing is is that rats
don't just play once they play many many
many times and that's also the case with
human beings is that you don't just play
once you play many many times and there
is a difference between the rules of a
game and the rules of a set of games and
that's so unbelievably important so you
keep that mind because we'll return to
that so anyways the next time the two
rats get together the little rat has to
ask the big rat to play because the rule
basically is subordinate entity asks
dominant entity to play and so the
little rat does what mammals do to play
you know they kind of put their paws
down and put the rear end up bit up in
the air you see dogs do that and unless
you're completely clueless you know that
that doesn't mean he's going for your
throat means he wants you to whack him
on the side of the head so he can sort
of pretend to bite you you know it's
it's pretty obvious if you've played
with dogs and children so and I make
that comparison because dogs and
children understand each other right
they're pack animals they follow the
same basic rules they know how to play
they can become friends otherwise you
wouldn't have them as pets I mean the
dogs not the children so anyways the
little rat asks the big rot to play and
the big rat things yeah yeah okay they
will play they wrestle and you pair them
multiple times well if you pair them
multiple times what you find is that
less the big rat lets the little rat win
thirty percent of the time the little
rat
won't ask the big rat to play anymore
and that do you think well who cares
what like why is that important it's
like it's really important that's a
really important discovery because it
shows you that that even rats have a set
set a sense of fair play that emerges
across iterated games it's it's it's an
ever it's evidence for the biological
instantiation of a social morality it's
a big deal man that's a big discovery
and and it shows you that even at the
level of rats they're very social
animals by the way the interactions
between rats are are mediated by
something like a sense of fairness or
justice and so that's extremely cool
because you know we tend to think of
animals as having dominance hierarchies
and that's predicated on power and that
idea even though the bloody postmodern
is still believed in biology they extend
that analogy up to human beings it's
just not true ok well the same turns out
to be true of chimpanzees so friends de
Waal who's a Dutch primatologist a very
smart one too he's been interested in
the biological basis of morality as well
and he's written a lot of good books on
primate behavior chimps in particular
chimps are brutal creatures man-like
they go to war eh and so in if you have
a chimp territory out in the jungle then
the juveniles will the males in
particular
they'll band together in groups of four
or five is often but not always a female
or two with them and if they come across
chimps from another troop that aren't
within their hierarchy let's say they
will if they're if they outnumber them
because they can't really count but they
can estimate magnitude visually it's not
the same as counting but if they
outnumber them they will tear them to
pieces and chimps are at least twice as
strong as a really well developed human
male and so they can tear you up pretty
good and chimps are perfectly capable
they hunt there they're carnivorous like
human beings and they hunt they hunt
colobus monkeys often they weigh about
40 pounds and they'll basically eat them
alive but the monkeys screaming away
like mad because you know it's in pain
because it's being eaten and that
doesn't slow the chimps down a bit
there's no cross species empathy
stopping them from having their
knack and so chimps are very brutal
creatures and it isn't obvious they have
a lot of internal inhibition of their
aggression at all most of the inhibition
is Sociological it's out in the
hierarchy and so the reason chimps
aren't always aggressive with one
another is because they know who can
pound them and and who will gang up on
them and who won't they establish their
hierarchy anyways you know you think
about a chimp hierarchy and you're
talking about a fairly strong and
aggressive creature you might think its
biggest ugliest meanest most vicious
irritable unpleasant chimp that rises to
the top well that's kind of the
postmodernist view of human society but
that's not the case it happens sometimes
but what happens and DeWall has
documented this quite nicely is that
tyrant chimps lead unstable regimes now
you know you that might sound familiar
because the same thing of course is true
of human beings and why is that well
it's because you know people don't like
tyrants chimps don't like them that much
either and chimps are actually quite
reciprocal in their social interactions
so they don't just dominate each other
they groom each other they have
friendships they can track social
relationships over very long periods of
time no and and they do that and so they
engage in in reciprocal interactions
let's say pro-social in reciprocal
interactions and you might think well
what's the what's the weak point of the
biggest ugliest toughest chimp in the
troop and that is he doesn't have any
friends and so you know maybe he has a
bad day he's a little hungover whatever
from eating fermented bananas or
whatever he is
partying with and two of the slightly
less uglies less slightly less mean
chimps decide well this is a good time
to take them out and they tear them to
pieces and so one of the things do all
is pointed out quite nicely is that if
you want to have a stable chimp
dominance hierarchy let's call it a
regime the stable ones aren't ruled by
the tyrants because the tyrants get
taken out by by paired up friendship
dyad something like that so that's
really worth thinking about too
you know because
because it indicates that even in
creatures that have less complex
sociological orders and they do because
one of the things that predicts how
complex your social order is is how big
your brain is compared to your body
it's a encephalization essentially and
the more encephalitis the creature the
larger the social groups it can track
and of course human beings are very
highly in cephalo so we have quite
complicated group we have quite
complicated group organizations but even
in simpler group organizations like the
chimps it isn't the tyrant who rules
stabili and that turns out to be also
incredibly important okay so mmm-hmm
so you know so much for the idea that
power is the only game in town
then you got to ask the question is well
this is actually a postmodern question
so you know get one of the things
Derrida said the main postmodern Joker
is that by categorizing you you you
privilege one concept and you prep you
for saw the concepts out to the margins
and so he believed that when you
constructed a hierarchy of power that
the hierarchy of power privileged
certain people and marginalized others
and you know that's really not that
brilliant at observation as far as I'm
concerned it's rather commonplace all it
means is that when you categorize
something that there are things that are
in the category and a bunch of things
that aren't and so you actually can't
categorize anything which meant means
you can't perceive anything which means
you can't think or live without making
some things in the middle and everything
else on the outside it's it's part of
categorization itself and so maybe the
post modernists would go far enough to
question the utility of categorization
itself and I think to some degree they
do they do that but um
the point here is is that if you you
asked why it is that you would if you
were a postmodernist yourself why it is
that you would privilege the idea of
power above all else it's exactly what
is it that you're pushing to the margin
and so that's something that we're going
to talk about now here's one thing you
might push to the margin let's say that
you believe that hierarchies are a
consequence of power well then you push
competence to the margin and then
applying the post moderate mark
modernist logic you might say well the
reason your privileges so that you could
produce so that you could push
competence to the margin and so you want
to keep that in mind too because that's
going to become important as we discuss
the relationship between post-modernism
and Marxism maybe you're after the
destruction of the idea of competence
itself
all right so pro game postmoderns and we
talked about it a little bit we'll
return to it now we're going to talk a
little bit about Marxism I've got a
quote here from Marx the proletarians
have nothing to lose but their chains
well that was pretty good for like 1880
or 1890 or whenever it was he wrote it
somewhere around that period of time
turned out the proletarians had a lot
more to lose than their chains
they had their lives and their families
to lose and that was demonstrated amply
as a consequence of the what would you
call it the sociological movements that
were put into place when the marxist
presuppositions began to govern
societies like the soviet union so all
right so let's take the same post
modernist approach so here's some basic
tenets of Marxism its burgeois Xia
against proletariat the version was the
year the capitalist the property owners
those sorts of people the proletariat
working-class for all intents and
purposes the basic idea is that history
itself is nothing but the what would you
call it the documentation of the
struggle of one class against the other
okay no like that's wrong but it's okay
because it's too simple obviously it's
obviously too simple there's all sorts
of motivations that people have some of
them are economic
some of them are associated with power
but that's okay we'll leave that let's
give the devil his due and say well yeah
fair enough there's still a fair bit of
tension between the haves and the
have-nots have-nots and maybe that was
even more intense in previous societies
than it is now and it's no there's no
doubt that economics plays a role in in
virtually everything that human beings
do in a fairly significant role so let's
let's accept that as a potential theory
it's it's simple but maybe it's
practically useful and then there's kind
of an offshoot of that theory which is
that well if you're a Marxist that means
you have sympathy for the working class
right because that's what you're saying
all the time it's like well the poor
working class they're all oppressed the
poor poor proletariat you know and and
then you're also saying well we're the
good guys because we're standing on the
side of the oppressed and so then you
might also ask what your marginalizing
when you claim that you're the good guys
because one of the things that you would
be marginalizing is all of the ways in
which you're not the good guys but we
can leave that aside for a moment too so
but there's the claims is that you know
there's the working class against the
ruling class another claim is the ruling
class is the ruling class because they
exploit the working class basically
stealing their excess labor from them
another very very what surface lis
attractive claim that lacks any
reasonable justification you know
because it's predicated on the idea of
the world as a zero-sum game and clearly
the world is not a zero-sum game so when
someone creates wealth when someone is
wealthy it can be at least at times
because they created it not because they
swiped it from someone else I think you
know you can think of someone like Bill
Gates or Steve Jobs is a good example of
that you know they're there what they
produced had a value that far exceeded
what they garnered as a consequence of
their production even though what they
garnered was very substantial so anyways
but we'll get like I said we're gonna
give the devil his due okay it's the
Burj huazi against the proletariat we'll
accept that it's class warfare is the
primary historical mover no problem now
but here's one I'm not willing to give
away so easily
ah we have sympathy for the working
class primarily and we're good because
of that no I'm not going to just like
give that away so simply so let's
investigate that a little bit let's see
if we can actually figure out if that's
true we'll say use a pragmatic approach
because I'm a pragmatist in that William
James sense or maybe you could think
about it even more deeply and anciently
there's a statement in the New Testament
I think it's by their fruits you shall
know them fine so we're gonna go walk
down that road before we do that so now
that's another thing you have to keep in
mind before we do that I want to make
one more detour okay so I like making
detours and then tangling them all back
together so I want to give you a bit of
a history of theories of suffering and
I'm going to compare the Marxist theory
of suffering to the judeo-christian
theory of suffering and the
judeo-christian would be and the reason
I'm doing that is because I think the
judeo-christian theory of suffering is
actually one of the foundation stones of
our entire culture and so it actually
matters why you think they're suffering
and so the story that describes the
entry of suffering into the world the
mythological story is the story in
Genesis the story of Adam and Eve and
basically what happens in the story of
Adam and Eve is Adam and Eve are
unconscious to begin with and they're
sort of in this paradisal state there's
no death or at least there's no
knowledge of death there's also no
knowledge of self and then Eve eats the
Apple that the serpent gives her and the
scales fall from her eyes and she gives
the Apple to Adam and heats it as well
so she makes him self conscious they
both wake up the first thing that
happens is they realize that they're
naked and they cover themselves up and
the second thing that happens as a
consequence of that realization is that
they come to know the difference between
good and evil and I mean that's a
insanely complicated story that's
dealing with a absolutely
incomprehensible number of complex
phenomena simultaneously but it
basically goes something like this is
that to be aware that you're naked is to
be aware of your
agility and your mortality when when you
have a nightmare about being naked in
front of a crowd it means that you're
exposed to the crowd all your flaws all
your mortal vulnerability is exposed to
the crowd for for them to see for you to
be ashamed of for them to judge that's
partly why we're all clothed that's
partly why human being how human why
clothing is a human universal there's
many human universals by the way
clothing is one of them although it's
used for many different purposes so Adam
and Eve cover themselves up and so it's
because they've realized that they're
that they're vulnerable they're naked
and vulnerable that's self-consciousness
human beings are self conscious animals
we're really the only self conscious
animals other animals have the
glimmerings of self-consciousness some
of them can identify themselves in a
mirror for example but we have whole
theories of ourselves we have whole
articulated verbal and philosophical
theories of what a human being is and
what we each are as individuals so
really those aren't in the same
conceptual universe it's a whole
different it's a qualitatively different
issue in the case of human beings we're
self conscious self consciousness loads
on trait neuroticism technically
speaking which means that
self-consciousness is primarily
something that manifests itself in the
form of negative emotion and we all know
that you're on stage you get
self-conscious is that a good thing
no you can get so self-conscious that
you're tongue-tied right it's not good
you don't want to be self-conscious on
stage or maybe ever
you get self-conscious in the in the
face of someone you're trying to impress
you turn all red you stammer
it's like self-consciousness is a rough
business it's no wonder because you know
yourself for the for the fragile fool
that you are it's even worse than that
because see it took me a long time to
figure out why it was that when Adam and
Eve woke up they also developed the
knowledge of good and evil I just
couldn't figure that out because didn't
make sense to me well how self
consciousness knowledge of vulnerability
and the knowledge of good and evil were
tangled together or even really what the
knowledge of good and evil meant but I
figured it out eventually I thought oh
get it I get it it was like a real
revelation to me as soon as you know
you're vulnerable you know the
difference between good and evil because
as soon as you know you're vulnerable
then you know everyone else is in a suit
you know that everyone else is
vulnerable you know how to hurt them and
so that means you can consciously know
how to bring suffering into being and
that's the knowledge of good and evil
and you know that because let's say that
you're really good at torturing people
and there's no doubt the number of
people in the audience who are actually
quite good at that and maybe you all
have a bit of an affinity for it if
you're married I'm sure your partner
would testify to that so if you're going
to hurt someone what you think
essentially is okay what would really
hurt me and then you think well I'll
just do that to them it's like that's
that's that's a that's a good theory
it's very sophisticated so anyways so
okay so what happens Adam and Eve wake
up they weren't supposed to do this God
told them that they are gonna be sorry
if they did that but they did it anyways
cuz that's what people are like and
because we always learn things that that
knock us out of our present paradises
right we're curious and we won't leave
things alone and maybe things are not so
bad and then you you know ask some
questions that maybe you're not so happy
about asking once you find the answer
and you fall out of your little paradise
into history and you got to work to set
things right again and anyways God gets
wind of this and and he chases Adam and
Eve out of the Garden of Eden but he
says some interesting things when he
chases them out he says all right now
you know what's the consequence of that
and he says to Adam you're gonna have to
work now that's cool that's really cool
well he is God after all you know also
he he knows what he's talking about he
says you're gonna have to work so why
would you have to work now that you knew
you were vulnerable well the answer that
is well if you know you're vulnerable
that stretches out into the future you
know you're going to die you know that
you're fragile it's like maybe all your
problems are solved right now you're all
sitting here you're safe you're not
hungry you don't want anything to drink
etc but what about tomorrow what about
next week or next month or ten years
from now it's like just because you got
all your problems solved for this second
doesn't mean you've got them solved for
the rest of your iterate
through time so you got to work and the
work is the sacrifice of the present for
the future and so that's exactly right
you have to work now you think see
what's interesting about that this is
the theory that I was going in it of
course God tells that Eve well you've
really you know screwed things up too
you're gonna have these big brain babies
and and that's a big problem you're
gonna suffer in childbirth and then
they're gonna be dependent on you
forever and because of that you're gonna
be dependent on this man that you just
woke up and that's not gonna be very
pleasant for either of you but tough
luck
and so that's it that's the curse in
some sense and it's exactly right but
the thing is there's a theory in there
there's an interesting theory of
suffering that's implicit in that story
and the theory of suffering is that
suffering is built into this structure
of self-conscious being it's built right
into the structure so if you're a self
conscious being that's your lot it isn't
someone else's fault it isn't a
consequence of sociological oppression
it isn't it a consequence of the fact
that our society isn't organized
properly it's just part of being alright
so that's a big deal because that's a
that's an important theory because one
of the questions is well well you know
why is there suffering what are you
gonna do about it and it's a big it's a
lot different if it's just the way it is
for you and if it's actually your fault
that he's suffering those are or maybe
it's the group's fault that you're
suffering those are major those theories
are really really different than in the
second story and Cain and Abel
Cain makes sacrifices to try to get it
in good with God and Abel make
sacrifices and the sacrifices are kind
of archaic from our perspective they're
burnt offerings so the smoke goes up
where God can detect it because he's up
there somewhere up there where the stars
are and God rejects Cain sacrifices and
we don't really know why but it kind of
looks like Cain is a second grader and
then God Cain goes and complains to God
and says like what kind of stupid
universe did you make here I'm breaking
myself in half trying to get things
together making the proper sacrifices
and nothing's gone well for me and Abel
well you know he's everything he touches
turns to gold everyone loves him he's
even a really good guy it's like so
annoying what's up with this place you
built and God tells Cain don't be coming
and telling me that the entire fabric of
reality is wrong because it isn't
working out for you says sin crouches at
your door like a like a sexually aroused
predatory cat that's basically the
metaphor that that God uses and he says
and you let it in and had it and let it
have its way with you
and that's really an interesting way of
putting it because what God says to Cain
is that you know you're all bitter and
resentful and really it's no wonder
because you know things aren't going
well for you and then you've got Abel
who's over shining you in every way and
but yeah it's your fault this terrible
thing waited at the door and you let it
in and then you entered into a creative
union with it and you produced something
as a consequence and that's this
tormented spirit that you have now and
it's polluting your relationship with
reality and that's why things aren't
working so out very well for you so go
put yourself together before you come
and tell me just exactly what's wrong
with the structure of reality and Cain
isn't very happy about that because
really is that really what you want to
hear that's right like you have more
misery than is necessary because you
really didn't put your act together and
you know it and you've done it
creatively and so Cain goes and kills
Abel that's the story of how resentment
enters the world and it's the first
story in the judeo-christian canon let's
say about actual human beings because
Adam and Eve were made by God so they
don't really count Cain and Abel were
born so that's something so that's a
reaction to suffering right the
necessity of sacrifice and the
consequence of the necessity of
sacrifice is that some sacrifices work
and others don't and then if your
sacrifices aren't met with the with the
good will of God let's say well then
that makes you angry well of course it
does you can
got out of the story if you want if
you're not happy with that kind of
mythological or narrative statement but
it doesn't really matter because the
whole point is is that if you make
sacrifices especially if there's
second-rate things aren't gonna go very
well for you and you're gonna get bitter
and resentful and murderous and maybe
genocide 'el and it's really interesting
you know because Cain has descendants
and if you bug if you transgress against
them they don't just kill you they kill
seven of you and then his later
descendants kill 49 of you there's this
exponential growth of murderous nasai
consequence of Cain's primary primal
fratricide and then the next story is
the flood and that's not an accident
there's nothing in those stories is an
accident
okay so now you've got two different
theories about the nature of suffering
you've got the one I just laid out it's
called the foundational story of
suffering and malevolence and you have
the Marxist story which is well there's
oppressed people and the reason they're
oppressed and suffering is because the
oppressors are oppressing them those are
not the same theories right and there's
a utopianism that's implicit in Marxism
which is if you could just get the damn
oppressors to stop oppressing the
oppressed then the utopia would arrive
and so not only are the oppressors
responsible for the suffering of the
poor they're also responsible for the
fact that the utopia isn't here for
everyone and so how reprehensible can
you get well then that certainly
justifies that degree of malevolence
justifies pretty much anything you'd
like to do to them so anyway so let's
take this apart in a little more detail
don't do the Marxists have sympathy for
the working-class George Orwell was
interested in this question and so he
wrote this book called Wiggin Road the
Whig and peer which I would highly
recommend it so on a reading list I made
it's on my website you can check that
out those are books that have been
particularly influential to me and so
Orwell was a socialist he wrote the book
for
left book club which published a kind of
a socialist book once a month or well by
the time he wrote this book he's already
awake you know by in the 1920s after the
Russian Revolution no one really knew
what to make of what was happening in
what would become the Soviet Union right
I mean it was after World War one planet
was in ashes Pro intents and purposes
the old aristocratic order was crumbling
it was a horror show and these
revolutionaries came out with these new
ideas and tried to give the in principle
give the working class a break and
everybody watched to see what would
happen and the honest people and the
intellectuals watched and I separate
them for a reason but by nineteen twenty
twenty-one twenty-two something like
that
it was obvious already that something
was rotten in the state of Denmark
Malcolm Muggeridge went over to the
Soviet Union to check out how the
collectivization of the farms was going
and he found out it was actually pretty
murderous right because what this what
the communists did was round up all the
successful farmers and raped them and
kill them and steal everything they had
and send them off to Siberia which
turned out actually to be a pretty bad
idea now you think you think about it
those people were or serfs not very long
before a couple of generations at most
they were so not much more than slaves
and some of them had risen up to the
point where the me had a nice brick
house and a couple of cows and maybe a
person working for them or two and there
was a small proportion of the
agriculturalists in the soviet union
that we're producing most of the food
and that's just how it goes because
that's a preeto distribution issue in
any field where there's human
productivity a small proportion of the
people produce almost all of the output
it's actually the square root of the
number of people in the field produce
half the output so if you have a hundred
farmers ten of them produce half the
food but if you have ten thousand a
hundred of them produce half the food
okay so what happens when you kill all
the good farmers you starve six million
Ukrainians to death in the 1930s and you
know that's not something that's all
that
widely known but if you want to provide
some additional fodder for your
nightmares you could go online and read
about what happened to the Ukrainians in
the 1930s so without underneath the
under the collectivization principles so
let's say you're a mother and you were
starving to death and so are your
children and you know the Communists had
come in and forcibly collectivized you
and then they took all the grain that
your collective farm had produced and
they shipped it all to the city saying
so that's all done and you think ok you
know the city's gotta eat and so then
you go out in the field to pick up the
grains that the harvesters missed so
that you can you know the ones that
they've been lying there they're not so
good there's not that many of them you
go out and glean you pick up the seeds
that weren't picked up so you can feed
your kids so they don't die and so
what's the punishment for that death
because you were obliged under the
collectivization orders to turn in any
additional grains that you happen to
pick off the ground to the authorities
so that they could be well who knows but
at least so you so they could be shipped
to the cities I suppose which is of
course absurd because of course that
would never happen but it was mostly so
that you could just actually die so ok
anyways back to the road to Wigan pier
now I'm gonna read you a little bit
about about from the book so Orwell went
out to this mining town in the northern
UK and coal miners or will had sympathy
for the working class he really worked
on that his whole life because he was a
middle class upper middle class snobby
type Englishman and he knew it and he
tried really hard to overcome that he he
he served in the Spanish Civil War he
wandered around as a he worked in
in in low end restaurant he worked as a
low-end worker in restaurants in Paris
and and in London he has a very good
book I think it's called down and out in
Paris in London that describes that he
was seriously committed dude and really
a smart guy and so he's going up to
these terrible towns
in the northern UK where the coal miners
worked and have their families and you
know they had hard lives they had hard
lives and that's just saying nothing you
know that coal miners that he met they
didn't have any teeth by the time they
were thirty he said the women he talked
you said teeth are just a misery it's
better to get rid of them as soon as you
can and and and they went and the man
went and mine coal and that was rough
you know they all have black lung by the
time they were 40 and they were they
were done fundamentally but here's a
just a bit a bit of a story about how
hard their lives were so they had to go
in the mines during the day so they
never saw the day so that's one thing
they had to go to the mines and then
they had their like not coal off the
walls that's hard with hammers and picks
and all of that and they had to move it
but that was that was their job but
there was the commute so here was the
commute so imagine that the typical
tunnel was about that high something
like that and the typical coal miner was
about that high that's a problem eh
because you got to walk through those
tunnels to get to work so you have to
walk like this then the question might
be well how far do you have to walk to
work and the answer is three and a half
miles and that's how far you have to
walk back from work after you put your
eight-hour shift in at the coal mine and
they don't get paid for the commute and
so huh or well said that was more or
less like climbing a small mountain in
the morning before you went to work and
then climbing another one at night
before you went home and so that was
just I mean believe me I'm telling you
very little about how tough their lives
were but that gives you a little flavor
like some one day like that for a modern
person you're just your dad or you wish
you were dead anyways and so Orwell
talks about going up there to stay and
terrible places he lived in while he was
up there and the terrible food he ate
and and the miserable wretched scenes
that he saw and here's one of the
miserable wretched scenes he's on a
train through the neighborhoods he says
the Train bore me away through the
monstrous scenery of slag heaps chimneys
piled scrap iron fouled canals paths of
Sindri mud crisscross by the prints of
clogs this was March
but the weather had been horribly cold
and everywhere there were mounds of
black and snow as we move slowly through
the outskirts of the town we passed row
after row of little gray slum houses
running at right angles to the
embankment at the back of one of the
houses a young woman was kneeling on the
stones poking a stick up the lead and
waste pipe which ran from the sink
inside in which I suppose was blocked I
had time to see everything about her her
sac apron her clumsy clogs her arms
reddened by the cold
she looked up as the train passed and I
was almost near enough to catch her eye
she had a round pale face the usual
exhausted face of the slum girl who's 25
and looks 40 thanks to miscarriages and
drudgery and at war for the second in
which I saw it the most desolate
hopeless expression I've ever seen it
struck me then that we meaning the
middle class at that time our mistake
and when we say that it isn't the same
for them as it would be for us and the
people bred in the slums can imagine
nothing but the slums for what I saw on
her face was by no means the ignorant
suffering of an animal she knew well
enough what was happening to her
understood as well as I did
how dreadful a destiny it was to be
kneeling there in the bitter cold on the
slimy stones of a slum backyard poking a
stick up a followed drainpipe all right
so Thor well rates the first part of the
book and it details the lives of these
people and then he makes an argument he
says like how can you read about this
how can you know about this without
having some sympathy for redistribution
schemes and social and socialist ideas
and so he's actually asking himself this
question it's not just a rhetorical
question he's I mean he's a serious guy
right he went he goes up there and he
tells you a story that you have to have
a heart of stone if you if you don't if
you read that you don't think man
something should be done about this it's
really awful
so he's set up this situation where your
sympathies are completely with the
people that he's describing
but socialism wasn't all that popular in
Britain at that time and and so and
socialists weren't all that popular with
Orwell didn't really like them that much
he was trying to figure out why that was
so this is what he wrote in the second
part of the book now this got him in a
lot of trouble they didn't want to
publish his damn book after he wrote the
second part but he fought with them and
he got it published and it's a classic
and and people still read it and you
should read it because it's a great book
and Orwell's a great writer and Orwell
is another one of those people that
intellectuals who woke up pretty early
in all Orwell wrote Animal Farm in 1984
he wrote 1984 and 1948 wrote Animal Farm
approximately around the same time he
knew what was happening under Stalin and
he wasn't afraid to say it but it was a
message that in some sense fell on deaf
ears especially among the intelligentsia
and there was complicated reasons for
that but but it wasn't like the facts
weren't there for people to see them if
they wanted to and has already said
Muggeridge Malcolm Muggeridge had made
it pretty clear in the 1920s and that
was widely publicized by the way
throughout the UK what was happening
during decolonization the cool Acts
being the farmers that I talked about
earlier who who had committed the
unspeakable sin of crawling out of their
serfs status over a couple of
generations to the point where they
weren't mere property and half starved
so this is what Orwell had to say about
Socialists it might be said however that
even if the theoretical oriented book
trained socialist is not a working man
himself at least he is actuated by a
love of the working class
he's endeavoring to shed his burgeois
status and fight on the side of the
proletariat obviously that must be his
motive but is it sometimes I look at a
socialist the intellectual tract writing
type of socialist with his pull over his
fuzzy hair and his Marxist quotation and
wonder what the devil is motive
it's really difficult to believe that
it's a love of anybody especially of the
working class from whom he is of all
people the furthest removed the truth is
that too many people calling them
socialists revolution does not mean a
movement of the masses with which they
hope to associate themselves it means
instead a set of reforms which we the
clever ones are going to impose upon
them the lower orders on the other hand
it would be a mistake to regard the book
train socialists as a bloodless creature
entirely incapable of emotion though
seldom giving much evidence of affection
for the exploited is perfectly capable
of displaying hatred sort of queer
theoretical in vacuo hatred against the
exploiters hence the grand old socialist
sport of denouncing the brew Swasey it
is strange how easily almost any
socialist writer can lash himself into
frenzies of rage against the class to
which by birth or by adoption he himself
almost invariably belongs now I worked
for the NDP when I was a kid and I had
privileged access to the leadership for
provincially and federally for reasons
that I won't go into and I thought that
many of them were honorable people who
were really striving to give the
working-class of voice and I believe
that the working-class needs a voice a
political voice for obvious reasons I
think the Democrats in the United States
have made an absolutely dreadful abysmal
mistake replacing their working-class
political ethos with identity politics
we're going to talk about that and and I
don't think the situation has changed
that much I think one of the things
that's happened in the United States is
that world stability and peace in some
ways has been purchased at the expense
of North American working class
well-being no because the Chinese have
got rich compared to thirty years ago
forty year
go fifty years ago the in the Indians
have got rich again same comparison
basis there's more middle-class people
in India now than there on the United
States the trade arrangements that have
been in North America allowed for the
rise of middle classes globally at the
same time they opened up the working
class in North America to competition
from those low-wage sources and maybe
that's a good deal it's hard to say
right because it's not such a bad thing
that the Chinese aren't starving and
it's not such a bad thing that the
Indians aren't starving and that those
societies are transforming themselves
actually into communities that are quite
wealthy
it's like hooray for that it's an
absolutely miraculous transformation
it's the most rapid growth of human
wealth in the history of humanity so we
should be pretty happy about that but we
should also remember at least to some
degree who's paid the price for it and
so as far as I'm concerned the working
class needs a voice and it isn't obvious
that they have one at the moment
having said that however it isn't
obvious to me at all that the people who
purport to stand for the working class
actually do so or that if they do so
that the reason they do so is because
they're all compassionate and
sympathetic and loving and kind and
saint-like I'm more convinced by
Orwell's argument so back to the NDP the
people I met at the leadership level a
lot of them I had a fair bit of
admiration for but as I worked with the
party over about a five year period
there is this contradiction that came
kept emerging for me and that was that I
didn't really like the low-level party
functionary activist types like they
just weren't personally appealing to me
they seemed peevish and resentful and
then at the same time I was going to
college I was about 17 I got elected to
the sit on the College Board of
Governors and at that time Alberta was
conservative politically right it still
is of course but the it was part of the
Progressive
empire because they ruled Alberta
forever and all the board of governor
members were basically nominees right
they were conservative nominees so these
were conservative people and I was an
MVP member and I thought when I'd worked
for small businessman too who weren't
NDP they were they were conservative he
can never figure that out but I'll tell
you about that in a minute but I had a
bad case of cognitive dissonance because
they actually turned out that I admired
the people on the Board of Governors and
they were mostly it was in Grand Prairie
it's not a very big place and it's not
very old and so if you were reasonably
successful in Grand Prairie the
probability that you would inherited
your money from the Rs 2 crore
aristocracy was like zero because there
wasn't one write it the whole damn town
was 50 years old so if you had any
influencer or wealth you were a small
businessmen small to middle sized
businessman and you'd you knew what you
were doing and I actually admired these
people I thought well that's not very
good I admire them and I don't share
their political views and then there's
these other people with whom I
hypothetically sure political views and
I don't admire them at all what's going
on and then I read road to Whig and peer
and I thought oh that's it they don't
like the poor they just hate the rich
it's not the same thing it's not the
same set of motivations and so let's say
that you're a post modernist and you
privilege compassion for the oppressed
think well what do you push to the
margins well what are you doing with all
your hatred and your resentment and your
evil it's like you don't have any of
that that's a bad theory that's a really
bad theory okay so fine so you can say
well yeah you can say that but I don't
buy it I still think that the people who
stand to speak for the oppressed or in
fact motivated by empathy and sympathy
their hearts are in the right place see
I don't really buy that either because I
don't really think generally speaking
that it's a credible claim for someone
to make that their heart is in the right
place now
you can ask that of yourself and if you
think your heart is in the right place
well more power to you you know I I I
can't see the halo from here however and
so given that you're just as malevolent
as your neighbor or maybe even more so
and that that's actually pretty
malevolent given the intrinsic nature of
human beings I can't help but wonder
what you're doing with all those traits
that you're not admitting to but you can
you could even object well you know
that's a pretty pessimistic view of
humankind
it's not by the way it's just not naive
but anyways you could object that and
you could say no actually the weight of
moral authority is in fact on the left
even the radical left with those who
identify with the oppressed and who are
working to better their conditions okay
fair enough so then let's say well let's
give those people some power and if
they're actually motivated by compassion
and empathy and desire for the working
class if you give them power and you
give their ideas power then as those
ideas unfold in real time you're gonna
find out like do things get better for
the working class let's say or do they
get worse because we could we could
consider that like an experiment we
could consider the outcome proof I I
don't know what else you would do I
don't know how else you would you would
come to your decision because it's just
theory till you see it happen now
Nietzsche said back in the eighteen late
1800s that after he said that God was
dead and I suppose that would also mean
the theory that of suffering that I
outlined at the beginning that is that
the basis of judeo-christian
civilization that God was dead and that
people had killed him and that we'd
never find enough water to wash away the
blood
it's a paraphrase but I've got the basic
message right and he also said there'll
be two consequences of that nihilism
because there's
transcendent meaning and a move to
totalitarianism because people can't
tolerate nihilism they said the most
likely pathway to totalitarianism would
be communism essentially he didn't quite
use those words but he meant that he
they words are close enough
he said socialism but I'm going to use
communism to distinguish in it
distinguish it from democratic socialism
and he said that probably tens of
hundreds of millions of people would die
in the 20th century as we played out
that experiment and then he said but it
might be worth it if we learn something
from it rough man
I mean and and unbelievable like I
cannot figure out how in the world he
knew that that was going to happen
especially so far in advance but
Dostoyevsky knew the same thing he wrote
this book called the Devils or the
possessed you could read that that's a
great book it takes about a hundred and
fifty pages to get going
but once it like everything everything
snaps together after that you know and
then it moves and it's basically his
prophecy about it's an examination of
the kind of person who had arisen in the
aftermath of the death of God in Russia
who would lead the Communist revolution
that's essentially it it's brilliant
it's it's it's terrifying and it's a
great intro to Solzhenitsyn's Gulag
Archipelago which describes what did
happen when those sort of people took
over the revolution so let's look at
what happened after the revolution and
we might say well this how about we
replicate the experiment a few times
because you know how it is if you're
running a scientific experiment you want
to find out what something does if you
allow it to behave you don't want to
just run it once because well maybe
there was something specific about those
conditions that led to the outcome you
want to generalize it across multiple
circumstances so we might say well let's
take this set of ideas and let's let's
run it on a large scale over a very long
period of time in a variety of
exceptionally diverse cultures and
languages so let's do that okay well we
could first start
with the with the Soviets people even
now because it's like the hundredth
anniversary of the Russian Revolution or
celebrating Lenin it's like that's not
good
that's like celebrating Hitler okay I'm
dead serious about that it's not good
and the fact that people can dare to
think that that's okay means that
there's something wrong with the way
that we look at history Lenin was a
monster and if you want to know about
that you can read souls and instance
writings about Lenin because they
Communist apologists say well it wasn't
Lenin Lenin was a good guy he was all
motivated by love of the working class
it's like well his henchman was Stalin
and if your henchman is Stalin you're
not a good guy and and Lenin was around
during the early collectivization and if
you read what he wrote you'll find out
that he is perfectly willing to have any
number of people die as long as his
ideological system could be brought into
being so there's no celebrating Lenin
there's no work cool young Marxist hip
revolutionaries and he's our Idol it's
like there's none of that not if you
know anything
not if you're decent well there was
death of the cool acts I told you about
that there was Ukrainian famine that's 6
million gone there there was the rise of
the gulag state because it turned out
that Russia the Soviet Union couldn't
run on the principles that it had that
it had laid down as sacrosanct they just
didn't work so you had to enslave
everybody and run your economy as a
slave state essentially and try not to
kill the people in the gulags so fast
that you can't suck some productive
labor out of them was the death of tens
of millions of people we don't even know
the estimates range from 15 to 60
million and like we won't give to
Picayune about the numbers because after
the first 10 million you kind of made
your point and the fact that we don't
know between 15 and 60 is actually an
indication of the horror of it because
our count is off by tens of millions
and that's only within the last century
and then there was the 1956 crackdown on
Hungary and the 1968 invasion of
Czechoslovakia then there was the whole
like thermonuclear Holocaust thing that
was going on at the same time in the
fact that in 1962 and in 1984 we were
seconds away from complete annihilation
right during the Cuban Missile Crisis
the keys were in the intercontinental
ballistic missile release systems and
Castro as he admitted to Jimmy Carter in
case any of you are Castro fans which
you shouldn't be that he was perfectly
willing to have Cuba annihilate it if it
would have meant the defeat of the
United States and then in 1984
approximately I may have the date
exactly wrong the Russians received an
indication from their early warning
systems that the Americans had launched
five thermonuclear missiles and one
Russian decided that it was a mistake
and refused to launch the retaliation
and he just died about two weeks ago so
you know that was pretty close
and so that was experiment number one
let's say that that wasn't good that
experiment let's put it that way it
wasn't good it was exactly the
antithesis of good it was precisely the
antithesis of good but that wasn't all I
mean there's the People's Republic of
China that's a different country like
seriously a different country right
different tradition different language
how many people died in China under Mao
no one knows same issue with the Soviet
Union
although mile was a bigger monster than
Stalin and that's that's impressive you
know because there's Hitler there's
Stalin and there's Mao and of the 3-mile
was probably the worst he's still
revered in China maybe that accounts for
their affinity for North Korea which
could still destroy us all the remnants
of that horrible state maybe a hundred
million people died in check
during the Great Leap Forward that's a
hell of a leap forward well maybe it
wasn't a hundred million you know maybe
it was only 40 million but as I said
before when you're counting in the tens
of millions your points already made and
then there was Cambodia and the killing
fields and Bulgaria East Germany and
Romania and the Democratic People's
Republic of Korea that's North Korea and
Vietnam and Ethiopia Hungary etc etc etc
it was never a successful communist
state Cuba I suppose came closest but it
was radically the Soviets poured money
into Cuba so that doesn't really count
so then the first question was well are
these Marxists motivated by love or
hatred
well is it love or hatred that produces
a hundred million dead people is that
enough evidence or not and if it's not
enough evidence if you think to yourself
well that's not enough evidence it was
never really given its proper a proper
try it's like well what would have been
a proper try see I always think when I
hear someone say that I know what you
think you think in your delusional
arrogance that you understand the
Marxist doctrines better than anyone
else ever has and that if you were the
one implementing those doctrines you
would have ushered in the utopia that's
what you mean when you say that and you
know there they say and there's an idea
in the New Testament that there's a sin
it's the sin against the holy ghost
if you commit that sin no one really
knows what it is
that you can't be forgiven and I would
say well if you want a candidate for the
sin against the Holy Ghost in the 21st
century
the statement communism real communism
was never tried with the underlying idea
that if you had been the person
implement
it would have worked I think that's a
pretty good contender for something for
which you should never be forgiven all
right so that's Marxism so let's go on
to post-modernism we talked a little bit
about it now hypothetically it's an
attitude of skepticism irony towards
rejection of grand narratives ideologies
and universalism criticizes objective
notions of reason human nature social
progress absolute truth and objective
reality it's predicated on the idea that
the reason that you categorize
especially that the reason that you
categorize is to marginalize you
categorize to marginalize to obtain
power powers pretty much all there is
there's other elements of post-modernism
one of them is that human nature is
merely a social construct see the reason
for that as far as I'm concerned and
this is a postmodern critique as well
I'm going to move the center to the
margin and the margin to the center's
why would you think that human nature is
only a social construct well here's why
it's because that means you could
construct it any way you want to that
was a very common idea among us among
the communists you know they that's why
Moll wanted to wipe out Chinese history
that's why the Red Guard went around in
China and tried to destroy everything
every element of China's history prior
to approximately 1960 at that great
culture thousands and thousands of years
old as well so you could bring in the
new man but what is the new man well was
whatever slave Mao happened to fantasize
about or it was the utopian person you
take your pick but like I said if you
take a look at the corpses you can
pretty much figure out which of those
two it was so what's up with these
people these deconstructionist sees post
modernists what are they up to exactly
well here's the first thing
they came about
pretty much when marxism was no longer
credible no longer tenable as an
intellectual asset of intellectual
propositions now if you were a French
intellectual you had to have a lot of
corpses piled at your feet before you
were willing to think that you were
wrong so here's an example I don't
remember his name he was the architect
of the killing fields in Cambodia
it wasn't Paul part it was one of his
advisers unfortunately I can't remember
his name
he took his PhD at the Sorbonne and he
developed the thesis set in the Sorbonne
what Marxist thesis that the cities were
parasites on on the land you know it's
an extension of the whole bourgeoisie
proletariat thing the cities were full
of bourgeois types educated and educated
parasites essentially who were doing
nothing but stealing what was rightly
the farmers so when he came back to
Cambodia he put that into action and
emptied out the cities and put all the
intellectuals and the city dwellers
either to death or to work which
generally resulted in death and killed
about one-sixth to one-quarter of the
population but he got his PhD from the
Sorbonne and that's a good story because
that's exactly how complicit the Western
leftist intellectuals were in
facilitating the horrors of the 20th
century and it's not like we've learned
anything since then quite the contrary
we just gone underground and that's what
I see that's what I see when I see
post-modernism so what happened was
despite the affinity of Western
intellectuals for Marxism maybe because
they weren't paid as much as bankers
let's say if we're being cynical about
it because I've often thought that if
you paid sociologists as much as
investment bankers they'd be capitalists
very rapidly
walls which is also to say that you may
under pay intellectuals at your peril
and you know that's actually dangerous
because one of the things that's
happening is that as the universities
have become corporatized and corrupted
in a variety of ways more and more of
the professor's are adjuncts right I
think it's up to 30 40 50 percent
something like that now they've got no
tenure they've got no job security and
they're paid like $24,000 a year it's
not a good idea to radicalize the people
that are teaching your children but
anyways by the end of the 60s so much
data on the catastrophic failures of
communism had accrued that even the most
intransigent of French intellectuals had
to admit that the jig was up but that's
a problem because that's the whole
ideology right that's the whole raison
d'etre
he says in this terrible alberta French
you're gonna just give that up what are
you gonna do after that well what
happened was post-modernism was invented
and so it's a sleight of hand as far as
I can tell so and and with
post-modernism identity politics and so
the postmodern transformation is well
we're a little wrong with the working
class thing turns out that communists
killed them all and capitalists make
them all rich and that's actually
exactly the opposite of what we
predicted but maybe there's still a way
this could be salvaged how about if we
we don't say working-class capitalists
we say oppressor oppressed well just
we'll just trance transform the
terminology a bit and we'll start
thinking about all the other ways that
people are oppressed and then and all
the other ways that people are
oppressors and then we can play the same
damn game under a new guise and now look
the post modernists were Marxist so
let's make no mistake
Derrida himself said that post-modernism
was a transformation of Marxism I'm not
making this up
the question is why well because you
could say well post-modernism is a valid
philosophical school and we'll get into
that for a minute and they make some
valid claims one of them for example
this is a central post modernist claim
is that there's an infinite number of
ways of interpreting the world and that
actually turns out to be technically
correct part of the reason that we've
had a very difficult time building
robots AI robots that can operate in the
real world is because perceiving the
real world turns out to be so difficult
that we really can't figure out how
human beings do it because it is
susceptible to an infinite number of
interpretations so that's actually
correct now I'm not going to give the
post modernists a tremendous amount of
credit for discovering that because it
was discovered simultaneously in about
five disciplines at pretty much the same
time but you give the devil his due so
so what's the logic it's something like
well there's an infinite number of
interpretations of the world you can't
tell which of those are canonically
correct correct the basic narrative of
human struggle is oppressor versus
oppressed we use category structures to
constrain that infinite number of
interpretations because the basic
narrative is oppressor versus oppressed
we choose those narratives that serve
our function as oppressors so it's
deeply cynical but credible you know and
you can say if you're not naive that
people are motivated by power and that
our interpretations of the world can be
self-serving I mean we do want to serve
ourselves after all because otherwise we
die and so and we are centered in one
place and so we can't see everything and
we're biased so so there is the
probability that the way that we look in
the world at the world will be tainted
by narrow self-interest and maybe even
tainted by in-group interests beyond
narrow individual self-interest and we
know the
is true but it's also not all bad you
know like we a good person takes care of
his or her family what does that mean
what means you prefer your family to
outsiders you we're gonna get rid of
that it's a form of prejudice like it
really is like your choice of sexual
partner is a form of prejudice right
I mean maybe it should be distributed in
an egalitarian manner hey that would be
a lot funnier if it isn't a possibility
like in in in in in Huxley's brave new
world that was the rule you you shared
yourself with whoever asked because it
was rude not to and you know what it is
actually rude not to it's seriously rude
now is that something you want to take
away from people you want that to be
distributed in an egalitarian fashion
how prejudiced are you when you choose
someone to sleep with you choose that
person and not everyone else it's the
ultimate in prejudice if you say well
that's not prejudicial oh yes it is you
usually go for the most attractive
partner you can find usually going for
the healthiest partner you go for the
best person you can find who can
tolerate you it's prejudicial in every
possible way so well so okay so your
self-serving and you construct a view of
the world that serves those self-serving
causes and some of that has to do with
power fair enough that doesn't mean it
all has to do with power though it means
that some of it has to do with power
it's like racism people are kind of
racist or maybe people prefer their
in-group it's not that easy or maybe
people prefer the familiar to the novel
you know that IAT that the social
psychologists have come up with implicit
association test that measures
unconscious bias we don't know what the
hell that measures the people who
invented that bloody thing they know we
don't know what it measures they know
it's not reliable they know it's not
valid enough to be used as an individual
diagnostic instrument that's technically
the case they also know that you can't
train people out of their own car
just biases because there is not much
difference between unconscious bias and
instantaneous perception but they don't
really care I've written to mahzarin
banaji he's one of the inventors of the
IAT several times saying how about you
come out in public and say what you
already know which is that people are
misusing your damned tests silence well
that's partly because her discipline
Social Psychology is a corrupt
discipline as the social psychologists
have discovered over the last four years
and be turning themselves inside out
trying to rectify which they haven't
anyways we're giving the devil his due
there's an infinite number of
interpretations of the world and it's
highly probable that you'll lay a
self-serving one on top of it yes and
also that'll serve the interests of your
group however you define that yes but it
only accounts for a fraction of your
behavior there's all sorts of other
things at work as well and you don't get
to reduce all human motivations to one
motivation power and then you might also
ask well why would you want to reduce
all human motivations to power it's so
you can use power that's why you can
justify the use of power that's force
you don't have to engage in civilize
debate you don't have to give a damn
about the facts especially if you're not
a postmodernist
because you don't believe in facts
anyways and you might ask well why don't
you a I'm not kidding I'm not kidding
postmodernists don't believe in facts
they believe that the idea of fact is
part of the power game that's place
played by the white dominated male
patriarchy to impose the tyrannical
structure of the patriarchy on the
oppressors it's like I'm not making this
stuff up it's embedded right in the
theory all you have to do is read it and
you find this out so they don't believe
in facts while facts would constrain the
use of power at least that's how it
looks to me okay so fine we gave the
devil is dude there's an infinite number
of interpretations and you're likely to
use biased compression algorithms on the
world and they're likely to be biased in
your favor true but
only partly true and the difference
between an ideologue and the thinker is
that a thinker knows the difference
between things that are only partly true
and things that are completely true
things are complicated like I like to
think everything is as complicated as a
military helicopter you have to like I
think it's eight hours of maintenance to
keep those things in the air for one
hour because they don't fly their rocks
they plummet it's really hard to keep
them in the air and there's full of
parts and and if you don't know all
those parts you don't go in there and
monkey about with them because it's just
wreck it and that's just a helicopter
like everything is way more complicated
than a helicopter so you don't just go
muck about in there hoping you're gonna
make it better that isn't how it works
you need to be competent all right so
look here's where the postmodernists are
wrong I think there's three places and
there's serious errors the first is that
there is an infinite number of
interpretations but there is not an
infinite number of viable
interpretations there's a very finite
number of viable interpretations and I
don't think that this is theory I think
that game theorists have already
demonstrated this to some degree and
it's going to be built into AI systems
very rapidly ok so what are the
constraints ok first of all you can't
have an interpretation that leads to
immediately to your death or you're dead
now if you want to be dead that's fine
but if you don't want to be then you got
a lot of limited options right you don't
get to run naked across an eight-lane
freeway at night blindfolded because
probably you'll be dead that's a bad
interpretation ok so you might say
because you're fragile and vulnerable
and mortal that there's a limited number
of ways that you can look at the world
that don't result in let's say death or
serious damage or agony that's a bad
thing
agony is a bad thing most people agree
on that so you're constrained by pain
and anxiety at least your
interpretations are constrained by pain
and anxiety and you know you can make
pain worse or better by thinking about
it to some degree but only to some
degree when push comes to shove
pain is your master okay so that's a big
constraint that's a big big constraint
well but the constraints are worse than
that because not only do you not get to
have an interpretation of the world that
produces anxiety and suffering right now
but you don't get to have an
interpretation of the world that if you
iterated across time produces pain and
suffering and so that's that's a big
problem because there's lots of you
could go out tonight and get yourself
blind drunk on cocaine and sleep with
six hookers and you know maybe that
maybe that would be a good night you
know you might not think about it being
so good tomorrow but then maybe you're
dead of AIDS in a year or maybe you're
addicted to cocaine or maybe you're a
street alcoholic or whatever it's like
as an iterable game that's a down hill
and the thing is you play iterated games
you don't play one you play iterated
games and so your interpretation of the
world has to be one that will sustain
multiple iterations across time because
you have to worry about 40 year old you
and sixty year old you and that's a big
problem that's a lot of used stretched
over a long period of time and it's
worse than that because it's not just
you it's like you and your family right
and not only so not only do you have to
take care of yourself now in a manner
that allows you to take care of yourself
when you're 40 you have to take care of
yourself now in a manner that takes care
of you when you're 40 so that other
people are happy to have you around now
and continually so that they'll
cooperate and compete with you in a
positive way and so that's getting
ridiculously complicated it's not just
you now and you in the future it's you
surrounded by other people doing the
same thing now and in the future and
there's a lot of other people it can't
even just be you and your family you
know like like the psychopathic burglar
mob that's just not gonna go so well
right other people are gonna object and
the world is gonna object and so fine
there's an infinite number of
interpretations that doesn't mean
there's an infinite number of viable
interpretations in fact there hardly any
there hardly any playable games now
Piaget Jean Piaget that developmental
psychologist is a very smart guy he
pointed out something very interesting
he said
now Janu ran a set of iterated games as
a competition and in one iterated game
the rule was you bloody well do what I
tell you to and the other one is well
we'll all get together and decide how
we're going to do this okay now we run
the competition I'll pay a Jays claim is
you do what I tell you fails and the
reason for that is I have to impose
force in order to keep you cooperating
and the imposition of force is a cost
it's an efficiency cost and across time
that efficiency cost is going to
multiply and the equilibrated state
solution which is the one where we all
agree it wins now that's worth thinking
about you think you think about that
locally so you've got you're trying to
organize your family you have a little
family conference about who's doing what
in the household and what are you if you
want peace and harmony and an iterated
game you get everybody to say well
here's the tasks and we they have to be
done people have to agree on that and
then you say well which task would you
do you have to do some how about you and
you know which task would you do and
everybody agrees and then you say well
unless you can come up with a better
solution that's the one we're gonna go
with and then people can be a little
resentful and angry about the conditions
of existence where they have to work but
they can't really blame that on anyone
else and maybe that's the best solution
you could come up with and that was PJ's
idea of the equilibrate state it was
like it's a voluntary agreement that can
be iterated across time that works at
multiple levels of social organization
man that's a serious serious serious set
of constraints and BSA by the way was
looking for a way to reconcile science
and religion he was looking for a
biological origin - morality and he
thought he found it in the idea of the
equilibrated state it's even deeper than
that so imagine this equilibrate the
state ideas actually there's something
to it
that if you set the state up properly it
will iterate across time so long that it
becomes a permanent part of the
environment a hierarchy is exactly
that's exactly what a hierarchy is
hierarchies are 350 million years old
they're not the patriarchal invention of
white European Christian males in the
last 300 years there
350 million years old they're stable
they're stable solutions to this
iterated game problem and they've been
around so long that were actually
adapted to them and that's part of the
reason we have archetypal
representations of the social structure
so and we also have archetypal
representations of the relationship of
the individual to the social structure
your job as an individual in
relationship to the social structure is
to embody the social structure but also
just serve as its eyes and its mouth so
that can update itself when necessary
so you take on the mantle of your father
let's say but he's dead
he's the past he can't see you can see
so you take the structure that's already
there and you modify it where it's
necessary and that modification process
is necessary or the state becomes too
static and collapses and that's why the
state has to be subordinate to the
individual and that's what Western
culture has discovered and we can't just
let them go that's the idea the logos
that's a big idea and you'd want to live
somewhere where you want to live
somewhere where the individual is
subordinate to the state it's like hey
go right ahead there's lots of places
like that man
emigrate go there 90% of the world's
countries are like that if you want to
live like that man go find out what it's
like you don't see immigration going
there that's for sure okay so that's a
big mistake that the postmodern is made
it's not trivial that's a big mistake
but it's not the only one well here's
another one they don't like inequality
but who does I'm against poverty you
know that's like classic protest sign
it's like really
it's like I'm Against Torture it's like
it's so obvious you don't get any
brownie points for being against poverty
no one in the right mind is for poverty
you know you ever watch The Simpsons you
ever see they're the Republican Party in
the Simpsons they all meet in an old
haunted castle at night with like
lightning bolts going off and there's a
vampire and a crazy text and then even
the Simpson Republicans don't sit around
in the haunted Tower at midnight saying
hey we need more poverty here's an
interesting thing so one of the
postmodernist claims is that diversity
is necessary and they make it racial and
they make it sexual they make it ethnic
and all of that that's actually
technically incorrect by the way because
I study individual differences so those
are the differences between people and I
know the literature so you know about
James des Morris memo right from Google
he wrote that part because he was
watching my videos which is why he
wanted me to interview him and I'm a
believer that there are biological
differences in temperament between men
and women apart from the other obvious
differences and that they're actually
not trivial and that they maximize in
the societies that have the most have
moved farthest to producing egalitarian
states the Scandinavian countries and
that the reason for that is that there's
two reasons why men and women differ in
temperament one is biological and the
other is environmental and if you remove
the environmental variation which you do
if you make the stadia latarian you
maximise the genetic variation and
that's been demonstrated in the
scientific literature over about four
decades and no one wanted it or hoped
for it and they weren't biased in
looking for it because that was exactly
the opposite of what social scientists
wanted to find because social scientists
lean heavily to the left and what they
wanted to find was you flatten out the
state so that everyone has equal
opportunity and the differences between
people disappear that is not what
happened the opposite happened that
wasn't wrong and no one was happy about
it and no one's happy about it now you
can actually
when you've discovered something in a
social science because you're not happy
about it
but if you take let's say there's a big
difference between men and women in
terms of trait agreeableness
compassion and politeness on average
women are more agreeable than men and
the difference is approximately this if
you take random pairs of men and women
out of the population let's say you had
to make a bet on who was more agreeable
if you bet that it was the woman you'd
be right 60% of the time well that's not
that much means you'd be wrong 40% of
the time that's almost 50% of the time
so this is a big difference by social
science standards but that's the
magnitude of the difference there are
some differences that are bigger like
the difference between men and women's
interest in people versus things is
actually bigger than that that's the
biggest difference we know but it's a
big difference let's say the agreeable
this difference but still they the
shared attributes of men and women far
outweigh the attributes that
differentiate them because you could ask
are there more differences within groups
or between them now the postmodern
answer to that is between them that's
why you need diversity by group right
that's why you need different races
that's why you need different
ethnicities and sexual preferences and
all of that well that's wrong there's
moral difference within the groups than
there is between them you don't get
diversity by crossing the groups you get
diversity by by selecting across
individuals in fact the idea that there
is more differences between groups that
there is between individuals is actually
the fundamental racist idea it's the
fundamental racist idea which is well
let's say you're Asian Oriental to use
the old word to discriminate the one
type of Asian say from the other you're
so different from me that there's no
overlap between our groups and you're
also so different and there's so little
difference within your group that now
that I know that you're not me you're
not one of mine I actually know what
you're like
no technically that's incorrect that's
wrong that isn't how you get diversity
now diversity is actually necessary
because people differ in intelligence
and they different temperament they
different skills and so you actually
need diversity because otherwise you
can't take advantage of all those
differences so you need diversity but
you need genuine diversity and like what
would genuine diversity mean if you're
trying to put together a work team you
want enough you want people of
sufficient diversity so that they more
or less so that you gather together the
appropriate talents to produce the
implement that's necessary to work
properly in the world
that's a competence marker because
otherwise your business is gonna fail
and so the proper diversity with regards
to employment is the diversity that
meets the the requirements of the
business essentially obviously that's
why you try to hire people carefully and
not randomly let's say third error first
errors there's only a finite number of
valid interpretations second error is
that there are real differences between
groups of people but there's more
difference within the groups than
between them third difference is social
status and payment especially in a free
democratic capitalist society is based
more on competence than on power in fact
we would say that when a person in a
hierarchy starts to act like their
position entitles them to power then
that hierarchy has become corrupt Harvey
Weinstein is a good example of that I'm
serious it's like he acts acted like a
tyrant what happened to him it's not
good not good for him what he did was
not good but it's an indication it's
revealed it's an indication that that
misuse so he's competent fine he gets to
have position because we need people who
are confident but that doesn't mean you
get to turn into a tire
if you turn into a tyrant then that
overshadows your competence and out you
go that's the definition of a
functioning state and our state
essentially functions it's not perfect
that's for sure
but compared to what that's the issue
compared to your hypothetical Marxist
utopia well compared to your
hypothetical Marxist utopia I mean we're
living in Osh wits but you're but your
actual Marxist utopia is
indistinguishable from Auschwitz so
we're not listening to that comparison
we're gonna take a look at what we have
and we're gonna compare it to other
places that actually existed in time and
geographically and by those criteria
it's like is there another time you'd
rather live another place you'd rather
live I mean a real place in a real time
I mean you want to live back in 1895
even in the Western world where the
average person lived on less than a
dollar a day and today is money you want
to live like those coal miners it's like
the answer to that snow if you have any
sense you should have some gratitude
that's another problem with the
postmodern neo-marxist like zero zero
zero gratitude it's all oh my god i'm
oppressed
of course you're oppressed but you're
not impressed by the patriarchy for
God's sake so you have status in a
hierarchy you might say well that's like
a reward so you're you're a high status
person it's a reward the reward should
be shared equally it's like a badge of
merit that you get it's a privilege it's
not the reason that in a capitalist
society filthy selfish capitalists put
you in the position so they can extract
maximum productivity from you and that's
exactly why you're there you get paid
you get paid so you keep working why do
we want you to work because your work is
actually valuable to us and so we're
gonna pay you so you don't quit it's not
a reward because you're a good guy it's
not a privilege that's not what it is
you don't hand those things out like
merit badges that's not how it works the
society is set up on selfish principles
we pay people who are competent so they
won't stop striving because we want what
they can produce so you don't just
distribute that like like it's a gift
it's not a gift it's not a gift at all
so that's another place where they're
wrong social status and payment is the
consequence of the selfish desire of
individuals and the group to extract
resources of intellect creativity and
industriousness from those who possess
them in excess now of course it's not a
hundred percent like that
there's incompetent people who rise to
the top you can fool people and you can
manipulate them and you can act like a
tyrant and you know we might say maybe
the system is like 30 percent warped
something like that it's not much more
than that because we can account for
people's success across life by looking
at their individual differences
intelligence conscientiousness emotional
stability creativity we can do a pretty
good job of predicting their trajectory
so there's error some of its health
right because sometimes you've got what
you need but you get cut off at the
knees or your family members do or you
know some tragic thing befalls you with
there's a randomness in this system that
accounts for a fair bit of it and then
there's a certain amount of corruption
fair enough
but not so much that the lights go off
okay what time is it 8:15 and I started
win sorry it's me 6:30
I should stop them
I'm gonna go for five more minutes and
then I'll wrap this up I want to talk
about intersectionality and and white
privilege a bit so so I first said well
we analyze Marxism we have analyzed
post-modernism I suggested that
post-modernism was a way for the Marxist
to keep going under a new guys I
suggested that Marxism was fundamentally
based on hatred rather than sympathy and
an empathy I suggested that the corpses
were the evidence for that I told you
why I think post-modernism is
fundamentally wrong but now I want to
talk to you a little bit about white
privilege so the first thing that I can
I haven't got this quite figured out
yeah I can't quite figure out why the
post modernists have made the canonical
distinctions they've made race ethnicity
sexual proclivity sexual gender identity
let's say those are four dimensions
along which people vary but there's a
very large number of dimensions along
which people vary right in fact given
that there's an infinite number of ways
of interpreting the world you could
immediately point out that there's an
infinite number of dimensions along
which people vary and so then the
postmodern question is why would you
privilege some of those dimensions over
the other and I would say well because
it sustains your bloody Marxist
interpretation that's why but you're not
gonna say that because it marginalizes
right
you've marginalized that so you can
ignore it so that's one of the fun
things about post-modernism you can you
can I have a very vulgar image in my
mind but I won't share that with you but
you can infer it here's some ways people
differ intelligence temperament
geography historical time you live now
and not a hundred years ago
attractiveness that's a big that's a big
one that's a big one but you imagine you
you could you won't go there either
you
he it's it's advantageous to be young
you've got potential it's advantageous
to be old you've got wealth health
that's a good one
sexes women have advantages men have
advantages maybe one has more than the
other it's not self-evident women live
about eight years longer they're
multi-orgasmic athleticism well family
structure friendship education well then
there's the classic you know postmodern
once race ethnicity etc why not those
other very dimensions of variation
there's no evidence that they're less
important in fact there's quite a bit of
evidence that they're more important so
like why not consider them then you get
intersectionality this is one of the
things that's really comical I think
because the post modernists identity
politics types actually realized this
they thought well okay race and gender
fair enough
what if your what if you're a black
woman that's a problem because well now
you've got two dimensions of
differentiation what the hell are we
gonna do about that and what if you're
what if you're gay and black and female
well then what if you're not very bright
and gay and black and female and then
what if you're ugly and not very bright
and gay and black and female and like
you can keep playing that game you can
keep playing that game an infinite
number of ways because there's an
infinite number of ways to categorize
things as the post modernist already
pointed out and so the intersectionality
theorist came along to plug the hole but
they don't know where they're going
they don't understand that the logical
conclusion of intersectionality is
individuality because there's so many
different ways of categorizing people's
advantages and disadvantages that if you
take that all the way out to the end you
say well the individual is the ultimate
minority and that's exactly right and
that's exactly what the West discovered
and you know the intersection list so
get there if they don't kill everyone
first so onto white privilege so it's
really interesting to find out where
these ideas come from because it's
usually the scholarship is so awful you
just cannot possibly believe it it's
just absolutely it wouldn't in
at the University of Toronto in the
psychology department the original paper
on white privilege wouldn't have
received a passing grade for the
hypothesis part of a undergraduate
honors thesis we're not even close
there's no methodology at all the person
who wrote it it was called white
privilege and male privilege a personal
account of coming to see correspondences
through work in women's studies well
first of all personal account is like
sorry no so she she listed a bunch of
ways that she thought she says these are
personal personal examples of her
unearned privilege or unearned privilege
that she saw as she experienced in the
1970s 1980s so this by the way that so
this idea is the opinion of one person
who wrote one paper that has absolutely
no empirical backing whatsoever which is
a set of hypotheses which has never been
subject to any statistical analysis like
if I ask you a bunch of questions it's
not obvious how many questions I'm
asking you because I could say how tall
are you
or I could say if you're laying on the
ground how extended would you be it's
like that two questions it's like no
it's one question
it's just asked two ways and the way you
figure out if you ask someone a bunch of
questions how many questions you're
asking them is by doing something called
a factor analysis which is kind of an
elementary form now of social science
investigation if you make a
questionnaire you have to subject it to
a factor analysis because you got to
find out how many questions you're
asking because you might think it's 60
but it's probably not it's probably five
that's the big five by the way anyways
who cares about that there's no such
thing as methodology anyways that's all
part of the oppressive white male
European patriarchy so we can just not
bother with that and we can pen a few
notes about how we think the world is
constructed and then we can screw up the
entire political system two decades
later okay so here's your white
privilege list some of it there's like
50 things I can if I wish arrange to be
in the company of people of my race most
of the time if I should need to move I
can be pretty sure of renting or
purchasing housing in an area which I
can afford and in which I would want to
live
that's actually a well thing by the way
I can be pretty sure that my neighbors
in such a location will be neutral or
pleasant to me I can go shopping alone
most of the time pretty well assured
that I will not be followed or harassed
I can turn on my television or open to
the front page of the paper and see
people of my waist race widely
represented when I'm told about our
national heritage or about civilization
I am shown that people of my color made
it what it is there's 50 of those I
think something like that okay is that
white privilege is that like majority
privilege is the same true you go to
China you're Chinese it's the same true
if you're Chinese this is a majority
privilege and if its majority privileges
like isn't that just part of living
within your culture so let's say you
live in your culture you're privileged
as a member of that culture well
obviously that's what the culture is for
that's what it's for why would you
bother building the damn thing if it
didn't accrue benefits to you now you
might say well one of the consequences
that it accrues fewer benefits to those
who aren't in the culture yeah but you
can't immediately associate that with
race you can't just do that say it's
white privileged there's many things
that could be certainly could be wealth
and the intersectional people have
already figured out that there's many
things it could be so like what the hell
seriously well what's going on well we
let these pseudo disciplines into the
university because we're stupid and
guilty seriously and they have no
methodological requirements and plenty
of power and plenty of time to produce
nonsensical research and produce like
resentful activists and now we're
bearing the fruits of that it's not
pretty so white privilege well the other
thing you might notice is that to
attribute to the individuals of a
community the attributes of that
community on the basis of their racial
identity is called racism that's what
racism is there's no other way of
defining it it's attributing to the
individual the characteristics of the
group as if the group was homogeneous
now the intersectional people have
already decided that's not a fair game
there's so many differences between
people but the postmodernist don't care
about logical coherence because they
regard logical coherence here it comes
again
as a creation of the white European male
patriarchal structure that's designed to
oppress the oppressed and that's
technically the case so logical in
coherence it doesn't matter and you
could say well if you act out your
logically incoherent ideas in the world
you're gonna run face first into a brick
wall and the postmodern answer to that
is there's actually no real world it's
all interpretation so there's no there's
no having that discussion but the post
modernists don't care because they don't
believe that discussion between people
of different power groups is possible
anyways so here we are well so I made a
case tonight you know I'll go over
what's the case the post modernists are
wrong they're philosophically naive
they're right about an infinite number
of interpretations and wrong about a
finite number of viable interpretations
and that's like that's that's death
that's the end of post modernist theory
and that's not the only way in which
they're wrong they're wrong in a bunch
of other ways but they're more
subsidiary the Marxists they're not just
wrong they're wrong and murderous or
wrong murderous and Jenna Seidel unless
you think murderous and Jenna Seidel
doesn't mean wrong and you you can think
that there's lots of would-be
revolutionaries who would be happy to
have blood running in the street if they
had their chance for revenge and the
opportunity to move up the hierarchy of
tyranny so you can you you don't have to
think that murder and genocide is wrong
especially if the right people are
murdered and genocided right that's
actually part of that part of the whole
equation but if you're willing to think
that murder and genocide on a mass scale
across many cultures over many decades
is wrong then Marxism is wrong and the
post modernists don't get to just come
along and a dot Marxism as a matter of
sleight of hand because they're marxist
theory didn't work out and they figured
out a rationalization they don't get to
get away with that because it's too
dangerous it's too dangerous to the rest
of us
and we don't and it isn't necessary for
us who are trying with the small part of
our hearts that might be oriented
towards the good to allow people who are
manipulating us with historical
ignorance and philosophical sleight of
hand to render us a goddamn guilty about
what our ancestors may or may not have
done so that we allow our shame and our
guilt to be to be used as tools to
manipulate us into accepting a feature
that we do not want to have and that's
[Applause]
it's that work okay
so we're just gonna do the we're gonna
move on to the Q&A now but before we do
the venue wants to do a little
announcement
sorry my name is Cameron we going the
the co managing director heard the
Chancellor as you are all leaving
tonight please be aware of something
that's come to light tonight outside the
building there is an individual
impersonating a UBC security guard it is
not in the building it was in the Rose
Garden there was no damage done nobody
was hurt
but there is an impersonator out there
so just please be aware of that thank
you very much so for those of you in the
first two rows you can either line up
here or at the mic over there and ask
your questions
and also try to keep it short because we
don't have that much time
hello Jordan B Peterson um huge fan in
your lectures use the term
post-modernism interchangeably with
cultural Marxism nihilism and moral
relativism I wonder if you've considered
or heard alternative beliefs that the
term post-modernism is not necessary is
necessarily always congruent on a
one-to-one scale these other terms and
in some limited circumstances is
positive specifically the idea that when
you use the term post-modernism to
vilify is by some others referred to as
pseudo modernism whereas some would call
what you endorsed to not be modernism
but in fact meta modernism
postmillennialism or post post-modernism
which unfortunately has a terrible name
and then I have very brief definitions
of those words if you need me to well no
as I said tonight you have to give the
devil his due and so we'll do that so
yes there is a very large number of ways
of interpreting the world there's no
doubt about that yes people use biased
interpretive lenses too as means of
interpreting the world to put their own
priorities forward without necessarily
knowing that they're doing so and that
that can corrupt them and society the
psychoanalysts figured that out way
before the post modernist so they don't
get any credit for that
like really none so it's useful to keep
those things in mind it's when they're
put but it's when they're put for it is
absolute truth that disturbs me it's
like yes people are probably racist they
might even be implicitly racist although
we don't know what that means and we
don't know how it's related to their
explicit behavior and we can't separate
it from in-group preference or
necessarily from reaction to novelty so
it's a tricky business you know
and we don't know how to separate
stereotypical racial perceptions from
perceptual heuristics we don't know how
to do that because you're always
oversimplifying the world because you're
not smart enough to live in the world as
it is you have to oversimplify it so yes
there are
times when post-modernism is useful i
used it quite useful ii tonight to
deconstruct post-modernism in fact so
but but weights when it's turned into an
absolute especially a moral absolute
that it and when it'll eyes itself with
Marxism it's like sorry guys know you
don't like grand narratives you don't
get to go there well that's where you
that isn't where you went that's where
you came from you never you never left
there so that's that's basically what i
have to say about that
thanks hello dr. peterson thank you very
much and my question is regarding ADHD
which is something i haven't heard you
speak a whole lot about maybe a little
bit now it seems to me that we or at
least maybe just me do not quite
understand ADHD too what could be its
full capacity maybe and because there's
many many voices saying that it's an
over diagnosed overblown small mental
variance that's prevalent in boys or
it's just young boys being young boys
and then there are some that would fight
and advocate for very different
treatment in the academic world and I
was wondering what you what your
thoughts are on ADHD itself and on the
whether you think it's over diagnosed
and maybe advice for me as someone who
has been diagnosed with ADHD on how to
overcome it without maybe becoming
completely reliant on prescribed
medication okay so first of all it's
definitely over diagnosed second it's
it's a very unreliable psychiatric
diagnosis many psychiatric diagnoses are
unreliable and that's because
psychiatric diagnosis aren't precisely
scientific categories they're weird
hybrids right first of all psychiatrists
aren't scientists they're engineers
engineers are trying to do something
rather than to describe the objective
world and psychiatrists are trying to
make people healthy whatever that means
it's actually partly ethical it's very
complicated
we don't know how to distinguish it from
temperamental variation so for example
if you're high in openness and high in
extraversion and low in
conscientiousness low and agreeableness
conscientiousness and and high in
neuroticism you're likely to manifest
symptoms of ADHD it's because you're
exploratory you don't like to sit down
you're full of ideas your attention
scatters across a wide variety of topics
and you're not very stable
temperamental variation it's also much
more common among boys panksepp showed
same guy with rats that if you deprive
young rats of rough and tumble play
which is what the young boys are
deprived of in school let's say that
they get hyperactive and then their
prefrontal cortexes don't develop very
well because they're not having the
right kind of experiences and that you
can treat that quite effectively with
psychomotor stimulants like ritalin so
that's kind of an interesting bit of
scientific information that no one pays
any attention to there is also
absolutely no evidence whatsoever that
long-term use of psychomotor stimulants
produces increases in cognitive gain
zero and there's plenty of evidence that
it's harmful so then the second part of
that was what about adjustments for in
the academic world say we disability
adjustments it's like that's a such a
rat's nest that I don't want to even
discuss it I mean it it I'll discuss it
for like 15 seconds there is a
never-ending multiplication of
disabilities that's what's happening
right now the disability offices and the
universities are swamped like I know
some people have it rough like believe
me I know that I was a problem I
seriously know that I've dealt with
extraordinarily damaged people in my
life here you're bloody hard pressed to
find someone who doesn't have a serious
problem or who doesn't have a
his problem in a close family member
it's like where do you draw the line
with regards to disabilities well you
can't you can't they multiply
just like LGBT identities multiply just
no really technically just like
that just like intersectionality
categories of oppression multiply it's
it's it's inevitable the way that you
deal with it is you have objective
standards you apply them to everyone not
because that's fair
it's not fair if you if your criteria
for fairness is that everyone has the
same outcome it's not fair at all it's
not even close to fair it's just less
tyrannical than the alternatives now we
don't know that yet because we haven't
seen the full range of the tyranny of
the alternatives manifest itself not in
our culture but it certainly did in
other cultures I think it's a bad idea
now I don't want to be absolute about
that like it's tricky you know because
if you have a disability that would
allow you to do the work in the
university and in the workplace with a
modification then perhaps the
modification could be made but I think
that was done a lot better when that was
in the hands of the professor's and not
in the hands of these crazy bureaucratic
structures that have risen up around the
disability issue
like they're one of the ten things that
are going to kill the universities or
maybe have already killed them possibly
because they mean they're walking
corpses as far as I can tell
zombies so and that might be wrong but
it's what it looks like to me first
thing I want to say thank you so much
those an amazing talk and I was
wondering if you could elaborate what I
noticed a lot ago here at UBC is that a
lot of students and young people they're
often desensitized to for example the
atrocities that communism or ideologies
that forced terrorism and maybe it's
some sort of Stockholm Syndrome that I'm
seeing where it's like people are just
their cat they're like trapped and they
can't do they feel in a way they can't
do anything about it and then they start
to like like like communism or they
start to see more social sort
socialist policy that in the end will
get them killed we'll get them hurt as
long as you kind of like elaborate down
on what you think can be done about that
or even if something can be done it will
not respect well I think something can
be done I mean I've been trying to
educate people about the horrors of the
Nazi regime and the Soviet regime in
particular I've concentrated mostly on
those two because but that's good enough
and trying to let people know that it
was through the fault of people much
like them that those systems arose and
and that there are steps you can take to
limit the probability that you would
participate in such a thing and that
those steps are associated with trying
to be truthful in your speech and
actions because the stability of those
systems depends on the willingness of
individuals to lie and and also on your
willingness to take responsibility for
the malevolence in your own heart that
manifests itself in those social
movements and so that when I don't when
I do my lectures when I do talks like
this when I put them on YouTube what I'm
trying to do is exactly that because
that was the best pathway forward
through such things that I could think
up over 20 years of thinking about it no
one is so habituated to suffering that
they can read the Gulag Archipelago
is actually quite hard to read without
having it affect them like your
psychopathic if that book doesn't affect
you you know it should if you read it
properly it affects you deeply and it's
not the only example of that kind of
literature so the people who are
habituated aren't they've just been
shown low resolution representations of
things they don't understand that look
vaguely bad they don't know a damn thing
about them and our education system has
done a tremendously appalling job of
educating young people about the ABB's
catastrophe of radical left isn't now
it's not much better with regards to say
the actions of the Nazis although I
would say on average people are more
aware of that but they don't but it's
shallow shallow knowledge so you make
the knowledge deep and deep knowledge
changes people and wakes them up you
know I mean the only reason that I ever
got convinced that they're that good and
evil were real more real than anything
else wasn't because I learned that good
was real that's hard that's that's hard
it's hard to learn that you have to find
examples of transcendent good you know
they're rare evil all you have to do is
look you read history a bit and read it
like it's about you and there's no way
that you can do that without a
transformation but people won't do it
it's like you want to imagine yourself
as an ostrich guard that's a rough thing
you see because you have to figure out
see young said if you confronted the
shadow which is the dark side of people
the aggressive side the malevolent side
that it it really reaches all the way
down to hell and Dante sort of was
trying to put forward the same thing
when he wrote the inferno right with the
levels of evil right because it was a
voyage through the levels of evil right
to the bottom he thought the bottom was
betrayal it's pretty good the most the
center of malevolence is betrayal I like
that because to betray someone you have
to get them to trust you and Trust is a
moral virtue
right especially if it's courageous
Trust because it it puts you in
alignment with other people and allows
you to move forward into life and if you
betray that you really it's like a knife
in that
it's like knife in the heart through the
back especially if it's someone who love
loves you betrays you and especially if
they betray you for your virtues that's
a really nice twist so I believe because
I think that people are capable of good
that if they know enough about evil that
that will straighten them out so but who
wants that you know this is one of the
things I really like about Jung he's
often regarded as a New Age thinker
that's wrong he's no New Age thinker
he knew that the the pathway to
enlightenment was barred by the
necessity of a passage through hell and
that no one was going to do that that's
why there isn't a world full of
enlightened people you might say like it
was just a matter of doing nice things
following your bliss let's say however
you might put it then why wouldn't
everyone walk up the stairway to heaven
that isn't how it works that's not how
it works at all I don't think you can be
convinced of the necessity for moral
action until you understand exactly how
dark and terrible things can get and
that it's your fault that they're
getting that way who wants to think that
so you can think it though but not not
without it burning you so thanks so much
hello dr. Peterson thank you for coming
we all appreciate it a lot I wanted to
get your opinion on censorship that
we're seeing on the web it's
accelerating you were a very notable
example you were locked out of your
Gmail and the entropic account part of
me oh yeah Trump's just got deleted by
an air in person you know now they're
saying that perhaps this was just a
contractor and you know maybe someone
from Twitter who's gone in a very far
left direction a YouTube has gone in
very far left direction I'm just
wondering I've started an alternative to
youtube called pew tube what kind of
what do you see for possible solutions
and just your thousand here's here's
it's a crazy thought but I'm gonna tell
it to you anyways so I was just reading
one of reycarts Wiles books I think it
was called how to make a mind I really
liked it actually
it helped me understand how the brain
compresses information because the world
is really complicated a so you have to
make a low-resolution representation of
it to live in it and he actually
explained to me in a way that I hadn't
really understood how the brain might do
that neurologically so that was cool but
you know kurtzweil is this guy who
thinks that he's a smart guy very smart
guy
and he's invented a fair bit of high-end
technical technological software and
hardware and he's the guy that thinks
that we're heading towards the
singularity and so the singularity is
you know how processing speed doubles
every 18 months and like hard disk
capacity every year and there's a bunch
of doublings going on a huge number of
them and they accelerate exponentially
and so it's probably we're probably
three years away maybe even less then
from building a computer that has the
capacity to make as many calculations as
reasonable estimates of the calculating
capacity of the human brain are
currently set at 18 months away two
years away something like that and then
we're eighteen months away from having
one that's twice that fast and then 18
months away from having one that's twice
as fast is that so that's like say six
years and and we've got something that's
eight times as smart as a human being
but there's a twist on that and this is
Kurt's wild twist which is as soon as
you make a machine smart enough to make
the next machine that's smarter than it
which is sort of what we're doing
because computers are so fast that that
will scale up to near infinite commuting
computing power almost instantaneously
now you think no probably not and Ellen
gates partner has written critiques of
kurtzweil and you know you might think
if something is impossible then it won't
happen even if you don't know why and
there's reasons to not think that that
will happen but Kurzweil is traced to
back the doubling of computing power way
before the existence of the transistor
and it's been ridiculously stable were
crazily stable so god only knows what
we're coming up with here you know and
you don't know what something of
infinite computing power might be like
like you seriously don't know and there
are serious people who are very very
very worried about that they're very
worried for example that companies like
Facebook and Google will manage that
first and you know those companies are
already making censorship AI bots and
that's not that smart it's
like making really fast robots that can
shoot people it's not that smart and
we're doing that too very rapidly and
you know I know some guys who worked in
advanced AI and you know how you look
you watch the term Terminator movies and
you see the robots that miss when they
shoot at you like they're not very
bright because the bright ones not only
shoot at where you are but they estimate
where you're gonna be when you make your
escape moves and they shoot there
simultaneously and their death rate is
100% and so there's no war against the
robots I mean when those things get
going they're gonna be so much faster
than us that will look like we're moving
through molasses to them so you know so
maybe what we're deciding now with all
of our individual decisions about
censorship in the way that we're going
to construct the world and all that is
exactly what kind of super intelligence
we're going to bring into being and I
would suggest that we try to bring one
in that's good and moral rather than one
that's evil and demonic right so what
can we do about that yeah there's only
one answer that as far as I know that
works is gay Rock together you're gonna
be the person who's working in AI right
I know some of these people it better be
good people cuz they're gonna build
whatever they're like into their
machines so they better have their heads
screwed on straight because they're
gonna get amplified like mad and I don't
like what's happening with Google and
Facebook and YouTube they're building
censorship BOTS predicated on a certain
kind of ideologies the kind of ideology
that we outlined today it's a very bad
idea hopefully good people will stop
that so then that what that means is
that your moral obligation is to be good
and the way you do that is first by
stopping being bad and everyone can do
that a little bit so I hope that's what
everyone does because the consequences
of not doing it are not going to be
pleasant they never are thank you
hi this question is about your biblical
lecture series I like that one because
it's about Genesis which is usually
ignored as being were this post
enlightenment society we don't need
these ancient creation myths and also I
thought revelations kind of gets the
same treatment as being dismissed
because it's the crazy hallucinogenic
trip of some isolated madman in the
middle of the Mediterranean mm-hmm so I
was wondering if after you're done with
Genesis if you were thinking about doing
revelations not without traversing the
geography in between okay
yeah I want to walk through the whole
thing if I can do that before I expire
so I mean I've read it and thought about
it and like it's such a strange book
because it's really big among the
evangelical Republican types and you'd
think really that really that's the book
that's but you rely have you read it
it's it's it's a it's it's a crazy
hallucinogenic trip
that's what revelation is no that's not
to play it down because god only knows
about crazy hallucinogenic trips that's
for sure I mean there's there's accruing
evidence I would say that a tremendous
amount of the religious orientation of
human beings you know that deep
mythological symbolic orientation is in
no small part a consequence of
humanity's experimentation with
psychedelic substances I think that's
that the evidence for that I think has
become virtually overwhelming so anyways
I will get there maybe probably not
because at the rate I'm going through
the first stories it'll take me forever
to get there really that's okay so thank
you dr. Peterson thank you first of all
it's great pleasure being here it's
awesome to see you live I basically got
into your works just earlier this year
and I had an original question but your
talk today kind of made me decide to
change my mind was can
ask do you feel as though would you
agree with me in the sentiment that the
left is pushed so hard for a total
control of our society over the last
however many years it's almost to a
point we're saying 2013 was a different
time would you say that because they
pushed so hard they've created this
backlash and the backlash created caused
them the backlash back again so they
doubled down with their ideology and
then they get they lose another argument
they lose another ideological war they
news lose another me more and they
double down again and they double down
again and again and they can't seem to
meme they can't seem to argue they can't
seem they can't they don't want to have
an intellectual discussion and as an
interpretation of what you were saying
there is no there's doesn't seem to be
any any any care of what's right with
them they just want power they just want
they just want to win do you would you
agree with the sentiment that they're
burning themselves out and creating the
mass red pilling of the conservative
movement that we see going on would you
possibly think that maybe they've
committed suicide and and talks like
this people like yourself ben shapiro
and others who talk to people like what
the subjects that we do the taboo of
nowadays possibly that this this is the
answer to defeat the the leftist
stranglehold it's not okay so first of
all well first of all the first
observation is a really interesting one
because you know that things can go out
of hand very very rapidly yeah and the
reason they do that is because of
positive feedback loops know the thing
that kurtzweil talks about is a positive
feedback loop an intelligent machine
makes another intelligent machine that
makes another intelligent machine that's
a positive feedback loop and that can
spiral upwards out of control very
rapidly and that's what polarization is
it's like I tap you you tap me I slap
you you punch me well up it goes well I
think that's partly why in the New
Testament for example there's an
injunction that's
turn the other cheek resist not evil
why because otherwise you get into a
positive feedback loop and then you
better look the hell out and things can
tilt very very rapidly I mean no you
have to do look at what happened in
World War one no one expected that it
was like one one relatively minor member
I think of the aristocracy if I remember
correctly was assassinated in one minor
little country it's like bang everything
fell apart and that's positive feedback
loops right and so that's what we're in
right now and we got to be and that's a
really chaotic time and so I would say
maintain self-control and don't aim to
win a matte piece because winning that's
that's not peace it's better dame for
peace you know I've got this tour coming
up in November 11th I'm quite worried
about it because I know there's going to
be protesters there and that they've
been emboldened by the fact that they
shot the talk down before and I want to
make a video I'll probably do it
tomorrow telling everyone that comes to
that meeting to like watch their bloody
step and stay out of the gutter because
you just we're at we're at we're at a
point now where under the wrong
circumstances if the wrong person does
the wrong thing that the consequences
will be very grave now we can't predict
which action is going to precipitate
that and or even if that will happen but
it's chaotic enough so that it could
happen so you know so govern yourselves
accordingly now the problem is is that
there are people who would be happy if
there was blood running in the street
they're the same sort of people that
shoot up high schools or kill innocent
you know elementary school kids just to
show what they're made of and what they
believe and that's a big problem but for
the rest of us like hopefully calmer
heads can prevail and so it really is
important not to win it's like fighting
with your wife you don't win you can't
because you have to live with her you
can't win but maybe you can solve the
problem and bring about peace and so
you gonna practice doing that practice
restraint now and remember too that
these people that you're talking about
who erotica leftist is most of the time
they're not like they're 95% like you
and if you pull them out of the mob
they're just like your your neighbors
nineteen year old kid who's kind of
clueless and rebellious right and who
you might even like you put them in the
mob it's a whole different thing and so
you got to remember that to out of fear
of social isolation no it's just that
they're possessed by these ideas but but
only partially you know you hardly find
it full-blooded absolutely committed
radical leftist activists you know like
there are some but not very many most of
it it's just fragmentary behavior and
you have to remember that like when the
students come out to protest me there's
a case particularly at McMaster I have
to remember these kids they're not much
different than my kids they are when
they're in a stupid mob behind a hammer
and sickle flag you know but but but you
don't want to make a low-resolution
homogeneous representation of them and
so and so you that's why again I think
instead of winning you turn to your own
development you turn to your own
development you do what you can to stop
doing the things that you're doing that
aren't good because you're not gonna
hurt anybody if you do that all you're
gonna do is help and otherwise you'll
participate in this polarization and
that's unless you want that and you know
there's a dark part of people that it's
part of the part that voted for Trump
would like to burn things to the ground
it's like to hell I know well how people
felt when they went into the voting
booth it was like Hillary Hillary to
hell with it
Trump you know and that's a that's a
hell of a thing to say to hell with it
you know although I could I could
certainly understand that sentiment so
we have to be careful and all of you
people who are here who are advocates of
free speech and who are theoretically
happy to come hear me speak it's like I
really do believe it I truly believe
this and this is
thing I learned in part from social Nets
and in part from youngest that the way
that you set the world straight is by
constraining the malevolence in your own
heart and that's no joke man that's no
easy thing and that's a good voyage for
people to go on if they want something
difficult and worthwhile to do so thank
you very much okay just quick time for
pictures so your unless your yours is
the last question
okay so sorry to everybody else but
you're the last one okay hi dr. Peterson
thanks for coming my question is a
little bit off-topic from everything
else tonight but I really want to hear
what you had to say about it
I work in Residence Life here at UBC and
in the community where I am we were
recently affected by a suicide of
someone who lived in our community and I
was upset about it not just because
obviously it's a horrible thing to have
happen but also because res life in the
university like they talk all this talk
about like self care and your mental
health is so important to us but then
things like this still happens so I
wanted to know like if you think like
what do you think the university should
be doing to keep stuff like this from
happening in the future well it's not
self-evident that it's the university's
responsibility and the reason for that
I'm not saying it isn't okay I'm saying
it's not self-evident that it is because
different institutions can only do so
many things you know and we're already
requiring that universities to educate
and to act as substitute parents
increasingly and to take on the role of
judge jury and executioner as there are
more what should be criminal cases being
handled within the university say
having said that you could ask the
broader question is will what do you do
to help people be sufficiently in love
with life so that they don't wish to end
it no and I've tried to puzzle through
that for a long time and that's partly
why I've written the things that I've
written it's partly why I've produced
the online programs that I've produced
no and so we know that if you do if you
have students do the future authoring
program for example they're much less
likely to drop out of university about
30% less likely and their grades go up
and that's especially true if they're
male and marginalized it has a bigger
impact on those communities and so you
know I've tried to get universities
interested now the doubt is there but
they're not and it's very difficult to
get a big bureaucracy to move a like big
big is a mobile so I'm not sure there's
anything they can really do about it
it's certainly possible that the things
that they're trying to do about it are
making it worse you know that's another
thing that you learn if you're a good
social scientist just like there was
evidence and I don't know if this is
still the case but but there was good
evidence I looked into this about 15
years ago say you want to prevent
suicides you put a suicide hotline in
your town and you advertise it what
happens suicide rate goes up because
you're advertising suicide right and
lots of lots of interventions are like
that it's really really hard to make
things better and it's really really
easy to make them worse and so that's
another problem you get these big
bureaucracies let's say and they're
hypothetically motivated by positive
intentions and I would say
hypothetically again because it takes an
awful lot of work to help someone
straight now it's no joke especially if
they're in real trouble and they put in
place these structures that are designed
to help but they don't ever evaluate
them and they could easily be making it
worse so so I don't have a
straightforward answer to that question
I think that well that's that's the only
answer I have yeah thank you okay
okay so that's the end of the show if
you're in the first two rows you can
stick around and get some pictures
otherwise drive safe and yeah
[Applause]